<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="spirit_of_laws_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<SOL>
    
<title>THE SPIRIT OF LAWS.</title> 

    <book>
        <heading>BOOK I. OF LAWS IN GENERAL.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
           <subheading>Of The Relation Of Laws To Different Beings.</subheading>
        <p>
            <laws type="general">LAWS, in their most general signification, are the necessary relations arising from the nature of things.</laws> In this sense, all beings have their [laws]; <laws type="religiously_driven">the Deity his* [laws]</laws>, the material world its [laws], the intelligence superior to man their [laws], the beasts their [laws], man his [laws].
            They who assert, that a blind fatality produced the various effects we behold in this world, talk very absurdly; for can any thing be more unreasonable than to pretend that a blind fatality could be productive of intelligent beings?
            There is then a primitive reason; <religious type="idea_or_belief">and [laws] are the relations subsisting between it and different beings, and the relations of these to one another.
            God is related to the universe as creator and preserver:</religious> the [laws] by which he created all things are those by which he preserves them. He acts according to these rules, because he knows them; he knows them, <laws type="religiously_driven">because he made them</laws>; and he made them, because <rationale type="logical">they are relative to his wisdom and power</rationale>.
            Since we observe that the world, though formed by the motion of matter, and void of understanding, subsists through so long a succession of ages, its motions must certainly be directed by invariable [laws]: and, could we imagine another world, it must also have constant rules, or it would inevitably perish.
            Thus the creation, which seems an arbitrary act, supposeth [laws] as invariable as those of the fatality of the atheists. It would be absurd to say, that the Creator might govern the world without those rules, since without them it could not subsist.
            <laws type="fixed">These rules are a fixed and invariable relation.</laws> In bodies moved, the <laws type="process">motion is received, increased, diminished, lost</laws>, according to the relations of the quantity of matter and velocity: each diversity is uniformity; each change is constancy.
            Particular intelligent beings may have [laws] of their own making; but they have some likewise which they never made. Before there were intelligent beings, they were possible; they had therefore possible relations, and consequently possible [laws]. Before [laws] were made, <rationale type="political">there were relations of possible justice</rationale>. To say that there is nothing just or unjust, but what is commanded or forbidden by positive [laws], is the same as saying that, before the describing of a circle, all the radii were not equal.
            We must therefore acknowledge relations of <rationale type="political">justice antecedent to the positive law by which they are established</rationale>: as for instance, that, if human societies existed, <rationale type="philosophy">it would be right to conform to their [laws]</rationale>; if there were intelligent beings that had received a benefit of another being, they ought to shew their gratitude; if one intelligent being had created another intelligent being, the latter ought to continue in its original state of dependence; if one intelligent being injures another, it deserves a retaliation; and so on.
            But the intelligent world is far from being so well governed as the physical: for, though the former has also its [laws], which of their own nature are invariable, it does not conform to them so exactly as the physical world. This is because, on the one hand, particular intelligent beings are of a finite nature, and consequently <rationale type="logical">liable to error</rationale>; and, on the other, <human_behavior type="human_nature">their nature requires them to be free agents</human_behavior>. Hence they do not steadily conform to their primitive [laws]; and even those of their own instituting they frequently infringe.
            Whether brutes be governed by the general [laws] of motion, or by a particular movement, we cannot determine. Be that as it may, they have not a more intimate relation to God than the rest of the material world; and sensation is of no other use to them, than in the relation they have either to other particular beings, or to themselves.
            <natural_law type="pursuit_of_happiness">By the allurement of pleasure they preserve the individual</natural_law>, and by the same allurement they preserve their species. They have natural [laws], because they are united by sensation; positive [laws] they have none, because they are not connected by knowledge: and yet they do not invariably conform to their natural [laws]: these are better observed by vegetables, that have neither understanding nor sense.
            Brutes are deprived of the high advantages which we have; but they have some which we have not. They have not our hopes; but they are without our fears: they are subject, like us, to death, but without knowing it: even most of them are more attentive than we to self-preservation, and do not make so bad a use of their passions.
            <driving_factors type="physical">Man, as a physical being, is, like other bodies, governed by invariable [laws].</driving_factors> <driving_factors type="mental">As an intelligent being, he incessantly transgresses the [laws] established by God, and changes those of his own instituting.</driving_factors> He is left to his private direction, though a limited being, and subject, like all finite intelligences, to ignorance and error: even his imperfect knowledge he loseth; and, as a sensible creature, he is hurried away by a thousand impetuous passions. Such a being might every instant forget his Creator; God has therefore reminded him of his duty by the [laws] of religion. Such a being is liable every moment to forget himself; philosophy has provided against this by the [laws] of morality. Formed to live in society, he might forget his fellow-creatures; legislators have, therefore, by political and civil [laws], confined him to his duty.
        </p>
    
         <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Laws Of Nature.</subheading>
        <p> 
            ANTECEDENT to the above-mentioned [laws] are those of <natural_law type="life">nature; so called because they derive their force entirely from our frame and existence</natural_law>. In order to have a perfect knowledge of these [laws], we must consider man before the establishment of society; <driving_factors type="societal">the [laws] received in such a state would be those of nature.</driving_factors>
            The law, which, impressing on our minds the idea of a Creator, inclines us toward him, is the first in importance, though not in order, of natural [laws].<rationale type="philosophy"> Man, in a state of nature, would have the faculty of knowing before he had acquired any knowledge.</rationale> Plain it is that his first ideas would not be of a speculative nature: he would think of the preservation of his being before he would investigate its original. Such a man would feel nothing in himself, at first, but impotency and weakness: his fears and apprehensions would be excessive; as appears from instances (were there any necessity of proving it) of savages found in forests* trembling at the motion of a leaf, and flying from every shadow.
            In this state, every man, instead of being sensible of his equality, would fancy himself inferior: there would, therefore, be no danger of their attacking one another; peace would be the first law of nature.
            The natural impulse, or desire, which <person type="Hobbes">Hobbes</person> attributes to mankind, of subduing one another, is far from being well founded. The idea of empire and dominion is so complex, and depends on so many other notions, that it could never be the first which occurred to the human understanding.
            <person type="Hobbes">Hobbes</person> enquires, “For what reason men go armed, and have locks and keys to fasten their doors, if they be not naturally in a state of war?” But is it not obvious, that he attributes to mankind, before the establishment of society, what can happen but in consequence of this establishment, which furnishes them with motives for hostile attacks and self-defence?
            Next to a sense of his weakness, man would soon find that of his wants. Hence, another law of nature would prompt him to seek for nourishment.
            Fear, I have observed, <human_behavior type="human_nature">would induce men to shun one another</human_behavior>; but the marks of this fear, being reciprocal, would soon engage them to associate. Besides, this association would quickly follow from the very pleasure one animal feels at the approach of another of the same species. Again, the attraction arising from the difference of sexes would enhance this pleasure, and the natural inclination they have for each other would form a third law.
            Beside the sense or instinct which man possesses in common with brutes, he has the advantage of acquired knowledge; and thence arises a second tie, which brutes have not. Mankind have therefore a new motive of uniting, <natural_law type="life">and a fourth law of nature results from the desire of living in society.</natural_law>
         </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Positive Laws.</subheading>
        <p>
            <driving_factors type="societal">AS soon as mankind enter into a state of society, they lose the sense of their weakness; equality ceases, and then commences the state of war.</driving_factors>
            Each particular society begins to feel its strength; <driving_factors type="international">whence arises a state of war betwixt different nations</driving_factors>. The individuals likewise of each society become sensible of their force: <rationale type="philosophy">hence the principal advantages of this society they endeavour to convert to their own emolument</rationale>; which constitutes a state of war betwixt individuals.
            <rationale type="logical">These two different kinds of states give rise to human [laws]</rationale>. Considered as inhabitants of so great a planet, which necessarily contains a variety of nations, they have [laws] relative to their mutual intercourse, <rationale type="philosophy">which is what we call the law of nations</rationale>. As members of a society that must be properly supported, <laws type="governmental">they have [laws] relative to the governors and the governed</laws>; and this we distinguish by the name of <rationale type="political">politic law</rationale>. They have also another sort of [laws], as they stand in relation to each other; by which is understood the civil law.
            The law of nations is naturally founded on this principle, that different nations ought in time of peace to do one another all the good they can, and in time of war as little injury as possible, without prejudicing their real interests.
            The object of war is victory; that of victory is conquest; and that of conquest, preservation. From this and the preceding principle all those rules are derived which constitute the law of nations.
            All countries have a law of nations, not excepting the <society type="city_state">Iroquois</society> themselves, though they devour their prisoners; for they send and receive ambassadors, and understand the rights of war and peace. The mischief is, that their law of nations is not founded on true principles.
            Besides the law of nations relating to all societies, there is a polity, or civil <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>, for each, particularly considered. No society can subsist without a form of government. “The united strength of individuals,” as Gravina well observes, “constitutes what we call the body politic.”
            The general strength may be in the hands of a single person, or of many. Some think that, nature having established paternal authority, the most natural government was that of a single person. But the example of paternal authority proves nothing: for, if the power of a father be relative to a single government, that of brothers after the death of a father, and that of cousin-germans after the decease of brothers, refer to a government of many. The political power necessarily comprehends the union of several families.
            Better is it to say, that the government most conformable to nature is that which best agrees with the humour and disposition of the people in whose favour it is established.
            The strength of individuals cannot be united without a conjunction of all their wills. “The conjunction of those wills,” as Gravina again very justly observes, “is what we call the civil state.”
            <rationale type="logical">Law in general is human reason</rationale>, inasmuch as it governs all the inhabitants of the earth; the political and civil [laws] of each nation ought to be only the particular cases in which human reason is applied.
            They should be adapted in such a manner to the people for whom they are framed, that it is a great chance if those of one nation suit another.
            They should be relative to the nature and principle of each government; whether they form it, as may be said of political [laws]; or whether they support it, as in the case of civil institutions.
            They should be relative to the climate of each country, to the quality of its soil, to its situation and extent, to the principal occupation of the natives, whether husbandmen, huntsmen, or shepherds: they should have a relation to the degree of liberty which the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents> will bear, to the religion of the inhabitants, to their inclinations, riches, numbers, commerce, manners, and customs. In fine, they have relations to each other, as also to their origin, to the intent of the legislator, and to the order of things on which they are established; in all which different lights they ought to be considered.
            This is what I have undertaken to perform in the following work. These relations I shall examine, since all these together constitute what I call the Spirit of Laws.
            I have not separated the political from the civil institutions; for, as I do not pretend to treat of [laws], but of their spirit, and as this spirit consists in the various relations which the [laws] may have to different objects, it is not so much my business to follow the natural order of [laws], as that of these relations and objects.
            I shall first examine the relations which [laws] have to the nature and principle of each government: and, as this principle has a strong influence on [laws], I shall make it my study to understand it thoroughly; and, if I can but once establish it, the [laws] will soon appear to flow from thence as from their source. I shall proceed afterwards to other more particular relations.
        </p>
    </book>
    
    <book>
        <heading>BOOK II. OF LAWS DIRECTLY DERIVED FROM THE NATURE OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Nature Of Three Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            THERE are three species of government; <governments type="groups_of_government">republican, monarchical, and despotic</governments>. In order to discover their nature, it is sufficient to recollect the common notion, which supposes three definitions, or rather three facts: 
            “<governments type="republic">That a republican government</governments> is that in which the <rationale type="political"> body or only a part of the people is possessed of the supreme power</rationale>: 
            <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, that in which <rationale type="political">a single person governs by fixed and established [laws]:</rationale> 
            a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, that in which <rationale type="political">a single person directs every thing by his own will and caprice.”</rationale>
            This is what I call the nature of each government: we must now inquire into those [laws] which directly conform to this nature, and consequently are the fundamental institutions.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Republican Government, And The Laws Relative To Democracy.</subheading>
        <p> 
            WHEN the body of the people is possessed of the supreme power, this is called a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. When the supreme power is lodged in the hands of a part of the people, it is then an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>.
            In a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> the people are in some respects the sovereign, and in others the subject.
            There can be no exercise of sovereignty but by their <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s, which are their own will: now, the sovereign’s will is the sovereign himself. The [laws], therefore, which establish the right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>, are fundamental to this government. And indeed it is as important to regulate, in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, in what manner, by whom, to whom, and concerning what, <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s are to be given, as it is, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, to know who is the prince, and after what manner he ought to govern.
            Libanius* says, that at “<place type="city">Athens</place> a stranger who intermeddled in the assemblies of the people was punished with death.” This is because such a man usurped the rights of sovereignty.
            It is an essential point, to fix the number of <natural_law type="freedoms">citizens who are to form the public assemblies</natural_law>; otherwise it would be uncertain whether the whole or only a part of the people had given their votes. At Sparta the number was fixed to ten thousand. But <place type="city">Rome</place>, designed by <person type="Providence">Providence</person> to rise from the weakest beginnings to the highest pitch of grandeur; <place type="city">Rome</place>, doomed to experience all the vicissitudes of fortune; <society type="city_state">Rome</society>, who had sometimes all her inhabitants without her walls, and sometimes all <place type="state">Italy</place> and a considerable part of the world within them; <place type="city">Rome</place>, I say, never fixed* the number; and this was one of the principal causes of her ruin.
            The people, in whom the supreme power resides, ought to have the management of every thing within their reach: what exceeds their abilities must be conducted by their ministers.
            But they cannot properly be said to have their ministers, without the power of nominating them: it is therefore a fundamental maxim, in this government, that the people should choose their ministers; that is, their magistrates.
            They have occasion, as well as monarchs, and even more so, to be directed by a council or senate. But, to have a proper confidence in these, they should have the choosing of the members; whether the election be made by themselves, as at <place type="city">Athens</place>; or by some magistrate deputed for that purpose, as on certain occasions was customary at <place type="city">Rome</place>.
            The people are extremely well qualified for choosing those whom they are to intrust with part of their authority. They have only to be determined by things to which they cannot be strangers, and by facts that are obvious to sense. They can tell when a person has fought many battles, and been crowned with success; they are therefore very capable of electing a general. They can tell when a judge is assiduous in his office, gives general satisfaction, and has never been charged with bribery: this is sufficient for choosing a prætor. They are struck with the magnificence or riches of a fellow-citizen: no more is requisite for electing an ædile. These are facts of which they can have better information in a public forum than a monarch in his palace. But are they capable of conducting an intricate affair, of seizing and improving the opportunity and critical moment of action? No; this surpasses their abilities.
            Should we doubt of the people’s natural capacity, in respect to the discernment of merit, we need only cast an eye on the series of surprising elections made by the <society type="city_state">Athenians</society> and <society type="city_state">Romans</society>; which no one surely will attribute to hazard.
            We know that, though the people of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> assumed to themselves the right of raising plebeians to public offices, yet they never would exert this power; and though, at <place type="city">Athens</place>, the magistrates were allowed, by the law of Aristides, to be elected from all the different classes of inhabitants, there never was a case, says Xenophon* , that the common people petitioned for employments which could endanger either their security or their glory.
            As most <human_behavior type="choice">citizens have sufficient abilities to choose</human_behavior>, though unqualified to be chosen, so the people, though capable of calling others to an account for their administration, are incapable of conducting the administration themselves.
            The public business must be carried on, with a certain motion, neither too quick nor too slow. But the motion of the people is always either too remiss or too violent. Sometimes, with a hundred thousand arms, they overturn all before them; and sometimes, with a hundred thousand feet, they creep like insects.
            In a popular state the inhabitants are divided into certain classes. It is in the manner of making this division that great legislators have signalized themselves; and it is on this the duration and prosperity of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> have ever depended.
            <person type="Servius">Servius Tullus</person> followed the spirit of <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> in the distribution of his classes. We find, in Livy,† and in Dionysius Halicarnasseus,‡ in what manner he lodged the right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> in the hands of the principal citizens. He had divided the people of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> into a hundred and ninety-three centuries, which formed six classes; and, ranking the rich, who were in smaller numbers, in the first centuries; and those in middling circumstances, who were more numerous, in the next, he flung the indigent multitude into the last; and, as each century had but one vote* , it was property rather than numbers that decided the elections.
            <person type="Solon">Solon</person> divided the people of <society type="city_state">Athens</society> into four classes. In this he was directed by the spirit of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, his intention not being to fix those who were to choose, but such as were eligible: therefore, leaving to every citizen the right of election, he made† the
            judges eligible from each of those four classes; but the magistrates he ordered to be chosen only out of the first three, consisting of persons of easy fortunes.
            As the division of those who have a right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is a fundamental law in <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, the manner also of giving this <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is another fundamental.
            The <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot is natural to <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, as that by choice is to <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>. The <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot is a method of electing that offends no one; but animates each
            citizen with the pleasing hope of serving his country.
            Yet, as this method is in itself defective, it has been the endeavour of the most eminent legislators to regulate and amend it.
            <person type="Solon">Solon</person> made a law, at <place type="city">Athens</place>, that military employments should be conferred by choice; but that senators and judges should be elected by lot.
            The same legislator ordained, that civil magistracies attended with great expence should be given by choice, and the others by lot.
            In order, however, to amend the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot, he made a rule, that none but those who presented themselves should be elected; that the person elected should be examined by judges,* and that every one should have a right to accuse him if he were unworthy of the office† : this participated at the same time of the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot, and of that by choice. When the time of their magistracy was expired, they were obliged to submit to another judgement in regard to their conduct. Persons utterly unqualified must have been extremely backward in giving in their names to be drawn by lot.
            The law which determines the manner of giving <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is likewise fundamental in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. It is a question of some importance, whether the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s ought to be public or secret. Cicero observes,‡ that the [laws]? which rendered them secret, towards the close of the <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, were the cause of its decline. But, as this is differently practised in different <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, I shall offer here my thoughts concerning this subject.
            The people’s <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s ought doubtless to be public§ ; and this should be considered as a fundamental law of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. The lower class ought to be directed by those of higher rank, and restrained within bounds by the gravity of eminent personages. Hence, by rendering the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s secret in the <society type="city_state">Roman republic</society>, all was lost: it was no longer possible to direct a populace that sought its own destruction. But, when the body of the nobles are to vote in an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>,* or in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> the senate,† as the business is then only to prevent intrigues, the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s cannot be too secret.
            Intriguing in a senate is dangerous: dangerous it is also in a body of nobles; but not so in the people, whose nature is to act through passion. In countries where they have no share in the government, we often see them as much inflamed on the account of an actor, as ever they could be for the welfare of the state. The misfortune of a <governments type="republic">republic</governments> is, when intrigues are at an end; which happens when the people are gained by bribery and corruption: in this case they grow indifferent to public affairs, and avarice
            becomes their predominant passion. Unconcerned about the government and every thing belonging to it, they quietly wait for their hire.
            It is likewise a fundamental law, in democracies, that <rights type="individual_rights">the people should have the sole power to enact [laws]</rights>. And yet there are a thousand occasions on which it is necessary the <rights type="legislative_rights">senate should have a power of decreeing: nay, it is frequently proper to make some trial of a law before it is established.</rights> The <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>s of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> and <society type="city_state">Athens</society> were excellent. The <rights type="legislative_rights">decrees of the senate‡ had the force of [laws] for the space of a year, but did not become perpetual till they were ratified by the consent of the people.</rights>
        </p>
        
       <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Laws Relative To The Nature Of Aristocracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> the supreme power is lodged in the hands of a certain number of persons. These are invested both with the legislative and executive authority; and the rest of the people are, in respect to them, the same as the subjects of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> in regard to the sovereign.
            They do not vote here by lot; for this would be productive of inconveniencies only. And indeed, in a government where the most mortifying distinctions are already established, though they were to be chosen by lot, still they would not cease to be odious: it is the nobleman they envy, and not the magistrate.
            When the nobility are numerous, there must be a senate to regulate the affairs which the body of nobles are incapable of deciding, and to prepare others for their decision. In this case it may be said, that the <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> is in some measure in the senate, the <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> in the body of the nobles, and the people are a cypher.
            It would be a very happy thing, in an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>, if the people, in some measure, could be raised from their state of annihilation. Thus, at Genoa, the bank of St. George being administered by the people* gives them a certain influence in the government, from whence their whole prosperity is derived.
            The senators ought by no means to have a right of naming their own members; for this would be the only way to perpetuate abuses. At <place type="city">Rome</place>, which in its early years was a kind of <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>, the senate did not fill up the vacant places in their own body: the new members were nominated by the* censors.
            In a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, the sudden rise of a private citizen to exorbitant power produces <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, or something more than <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>. In the latter, the [laws] have provided for, or in some measure adapted themselves to, the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>; and the principle of government checks the monarch: but, in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, where a private citizen has obtained an exorbitant power,† the abuse of this power is much greater, because the [laws] foresaw it not, and consequently made no provision against it.
            There is an exception to this rule, when the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents> is such as to have immediate need of a magistrate invested with an exorbitant power. Such was <society type="city_state">Rome</society> with her dictators; such is Venice with her state-inquisitors: these are formidable magistrates, who restore, as it were by violence, the state to its liberty. But how comes it that these magistracies are so very different in these two <governments type="republic">republics</governments>? It is because <society type="city_state">Rome</society> supported the remains of her <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> against the people; whereas Venice employs her state-inquisitors to maintain her <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> against the nobles. The consequence was, that at <place type="city">Rome</place> the dictatorship could be only of a short duration, as the people act through passion, and not with design. It was necessary that a magistracy of this kind 
            should be exercised with lustre and pomp; the business being to intimidate, and not to punish, the multitude. It was also proper that the dictator should be created only for some particular affair, and for this only should have an unlimited authority, as he was always created upon some sudden emergency. On the contrary, at Venice they have occasion for a permanent magistracy; for here it is that schemes may be set on foot, continued, suspended, and resumed; that the ambition of a single person becomes that of a family, and the ambition of one family that of many. They have occasion for a secret magistracy, the crimes they punish being hatched in secrecy and silence. This magistracy must have a general inquisition; for their business is not to remedy known disorders, but to prevent the unknown. In a word, the latter is designed to punish suspected crimes; whereas the former used rather menaces than punishment, even for crimes that were openly avowed.
            In all magistracies the greatness of the power must be compensated by the brevity of the duration. This most legislators have fixed to a year: a longer space would be dangerous, and a shorter would be contrary to the nature of government; for who is it that, in the management even of his domestic affairs, would be thus confined? At Ragusa* the chief magistrate of the <governments type="republic">republic</governments> is changed every month, the other officers every week, and the governor of the castle every day. But this can take place only in a small <governments type="republic">republic</governments> environed† by formidable powers, who might easily corrupt such petty and insignificant magistrates.
            The best <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> is that in which those who have no share in the legislature are so few and inconsiderable, that the governing party have no interest in oppressing them. Thus, when‡ <person type="Antipater">Antipater</person> made a law at <place type="city">Athens</place>, that whosoever was not worth two thousand drachms should have no power to vote, he formed, by this method, the best <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> possible; because this was so small a sum, as excluded very few, and not one of any rank or consideration in the city.
            <governments type="aristocracy">Aristocratical</governments> families ought, therefore, as much as possible, to level themselves, in appearance, with the people. The more an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> borders on <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, the nearer it approaches to perfection; and, in proportion as it draws towards <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, the more it is imperfect.
            But the most imperfect of all is that in which the part of the people that obeys is in a state of civil servitude to those who command; as the <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> of Poland, where the peasants are slaves to the nobility.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Relation Of Laws To The Nature Of Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE intermediate, subordinate, and dependent powers constitute the nature of <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> government; I mean of that in which a single person governs by fundamental [laws]. I said, the intermediate, subordinate, and dependent powers: and indeed, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the prince is the source of all power, political and civil. These fundamental [laws] necessarily suppose the intermediate channels through which the power flows; for, if there be only the momentary and capricious will of a single person to govern the state, nothing can be fixed, and of course there is no fundamental law.
            The most natural intermediate and subordinate power is that of the nobility. This, in some measure, seems to be essential to a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, whose fundamental maxim is, No monarch, no nobility; no nobility, no monarch: but there may be a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> prince.
            There are men who have endeavoured, in some countries in Europe, to suppress the jurisdiction of the nobility; not perceiving that they were driving at the very thing that was done by the parliament of England. Abolish the privileges of the lords, the clergy, and cities, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, and you will soon have a popular state, or else a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government.
            The courts of a considerable kingdom in Europe have, for many ages, been striking at the patrimonial jurisdiction of the lords and clergy. We do not pretend to censure these sage magistrates; but we leave it to the public to judge how far this may alter the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>.
            Far am I from being prejudiced in favour of the privileges of the clergy; however, I should be glad their jurisdiction were once fixed. The question is not, whether their jurisdiction was justly established; but, whether it be really established; whether it constitutes a part of the [laws] of the country, and is in every respect relative to those [laws]; whether, between two powers acknowledged independent, the conditions ought not to be reciprocal; and whether it be not equally the duty of a good subject to defend the prerogative of the prince, and to maintain the limits which from time immemorial he has prescribed to his authority.
            Though the ecclesiastic power be so dangerous in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, yet it is extremely proper in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, especially of the absolute kind. What would become of Spain and Portugal, since the subversion of their [laws], were it not for this only barrier against the incursions of arbitrary power? a barrier ever useful when there is no other: for, since a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government is productive of the most dreadful calamities to human nature, the very evil that restrains it is beneficial to the subject.
            In the same manner as the ocean, threatening to overflow the whole earth, is stopped by weeds and pebbles, that lie scattered along the shore; so monarchs, whose power seems unbounded, are restrained by the smallest obstacles, and suffer their natural pride to be subdued by supplication and prayer.
            The English, to favour their liberty, have abolished all the intermediate powers of which their <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> was composed. They have a great deal of reason to be jealous of this liberty: were they ever to be so unhappy as to lose it, they would be one of the most servile nations upon earth.
            Mr. Law, through ignorance both of a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> and <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>, was one of the greatest promoters of absolute power ever known in Europe. Besides the violent and extraordinary changes owing to his direction, he would fain suppress all the intermediate ranks, and abolish the political communities. He was dissolving* the <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> by his chimerical reimbursements, and seemed as if he even wanted to redeem the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>.
            It is not enough to have intermediate powers in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>; there must be also a depositary of the [laws]. This depositary can only be the judges of the supreme courts of justice, who promulge the new [laws], and revive the obsolete. The natural ignorance of the nobility, their indolence, and contempt of civil government, require there should be a body invested with a power of reviving and executing the [laws], which would be otherwise buried in oblivion. The prince’s council are not a proper depositary: they are naturally the depositary of the momentary will of the prince, and not of the fundamental [laws]. Besides, the prince’s council is continually changing; it is neither permanent nor numerous; neither has it a sufficient share of the confidence of the people; consequently it is incapable to set them right in difficult conjunctures, or to reduce them to proper obedience.
            Despotic governments, where there are no fundamental [laws], have no such kind of depositary. Hence it is that religion has generally so much influence in those countries, because it forms a kind of permanent depositary; and, if this cannot be said of religion, it may of the customs that are respected instead of [laws].
        </p>
        
       <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Laws Relative To The Nature Of A Despotic Government.</subheading>
       <p> 
        FROM the nature of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> power it follows, that the single person, invested with this power, commits the execution of it also to a single person. A man, whom his senses continually inform that he himself is every thing, and his subjects nothing, is naturally lazy, voluptuous, and ignorant. In consequence of this, he neglects the management of public affairs. But, were he to commit the administration to many, there would be continual disputes among them; each would form intrigues to be his first slave, and he would be obliged to take the reins into his own hands. It is, therefore, more natural for him to resign it to a vizir,* and to invest him with the same power as himself. The creation of a vizir is a fundamental law of this government.
        It is related of a pope, that he had started an infinite number of difficulties against his election, from a thorough conviction of his incapacity. At length he was prevailed on to accept of the pontificate, and resigned the administration entirely to his nephew. He was soon struck with surprize, and said, “I should never have thought that these things were so easy.” The same may be said of the princes of the East, who, being educated in a prison, where eunuchs corrupt their hearts and debase their understandings, and where they are frequently kept ignorant of their high rank, when drawn forth in order to be placed on the throne, they are at first confounded; but, as soon as they have chosen a vizir, and abandoned themselves in their seraglio to the most brutal passions, pursuing, in the midst of a prostituted court, every capricious extravagance, they could never have dreamt to find matters so easy.
        The more extensive the empire, the larger the seraglio; and consequently the more voluptuous the prince. Hence the more nations such a sovereign has to rule, the less he attends to the cares of government; the more important his affairs, the less he makes them the subject of his deliberations.
       </p>
    </book>
    
    <book>
        <heading>BOOK III. OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE THREE KINDS OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
            <subheading>Difference Between The Nature And Principle Of Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            AFTER having examined the laws relative to the nature of each government, we must investigate those which relate to its principle.
            There is this difference between* the nature and principle of government, that the former is that by which it is constituted, and the latter that by which it is made to act. One is its particular structure, and the other the <human_behavior type="human_nature">human passions</human_behavior> which set it in motion.
            Now, laws ought to be no less relative to the principle, than to the nature, of each government. We must therefore enquire into this principle, which shall be the subject of this third book.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Principle Of Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            I have already observed, that it is the nature of a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> government, that either the collective body of the people or particular families should be possessed of the supreme power: of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, that the prince should have this power, but, in the execution of it, should be directed by established laws: of a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, that a single person should rule according to his own will and caprice. This enables me to discover their three principles, which are naturally derived from thence. I shall begin with a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> government, and in particular with that of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Principle Of Democracy.</subheading>
        <p>
           THERE is no great share of probity necessary to support a <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> or <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government: the force of laws, in one, and the prince’s arm, in the other, are sufficient to direct and maintain the whole: but, in a popular state, one spring more is necessary, namely, <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
           What I have here advanced is confirmed by the unanimous testimony of historians, and is extremely agreeable to the nature of things. For, it is clear, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, where he, who commands the execution of the laws, generally thinks himself above them, there is less need of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> than in a popular government, where the person, entrusted with the execution of the laws, is sensible of his being subject to their direction.
           Clear it is, also, that a monarch, who, through bad advice or indolence, ceases to enforce the execution of the laws, may easily repair the evil; he has only to follow other advice, or to shake off this indolence. But when, in a popular government, there is a suspension of the laws, (as this can proceed only from the corruption of the republic,) the state is certainly undone.
           A very droll spectacle it was, in the last century, to behold the impotent efforts of the English towards the establishment of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. As they, who had a share in the direction of public affairs, were void of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>; as their ambition was enflamed by the success of the most daring of their members† ; as the prevailing parties were successively animated by the spirit of faction; the government was continually changing; the people, amazed at so many revolutions, in vain attempted to erect a commonwealth. At length, when the country had undergone the most violent shocks, they were obliged to have recourse to the very government which they had so wantonly proscribed.
           When <person type="Sylla">Sylla</person> thought of restoring <society type="city_state">Rome</society> to her liberty, this unhappy city was incapable of that blessing. She had only the feeble remains of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which were continually diminishing: instead of being roused out of her lethargy by Cæsar, Tiberius, Caius, Claudius, Nero, Domitian, she riveted every day her chains; if she struck some blows, her aim was at the tyrant, but not at the usurpation.
           The politic <society type="state_group">Greeks</society>, who lived under a popular government, knew no other support than <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>: the modern inhabitants of that country are entirely taken up with manufacture, commerce, finances, opulence, and luxury.
           When <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is banished, ambition invades the minds of those who are disposed to receive it, and avarice possesses the whole community. The objects of their desires are changed; what they were fond of before is become indifferent; they were free
           while under the restraint of laws, but they would fain now be free to act against law; and, as each citizen is like a slave who has run away from his master, what was a maxim of equity, he calls rigour; what was a rule of action, he stiles constraint; and to precaution he gives the name of fear. Frugality, and not the thirst of gain, now passes for avarice. Formerly, the wealth of individuals constituted the public treasure, but now this is become the patrimony of private persons. The members of the commonwealth riot on the public spoils, and its strength is only the power of a few and the licentiousness of many.
           <society type="city_state">Athens</society> was possessed of the same number of forces, when she triumphed so gloriously, and when, with so much infamy, she was inslaved. She had twenty thousand citizens§ when she defended the <society type="state_group">Greeks</society> against the <society type="state_group">Persians</society>, when she contended for empire with <society type="city_state">Sparta</society>, and invaded <place type="city">Sicily</place>. She had twenty thousand when <person type="Demetrius">Demetrius Phalereus</person> numbered them* , as slaves are told by the head in a market- place. When <person type="Philip">Philip</person> attempted to lord it over <place type="state">Greece</place>, and appeared at the gates of <place type="city">Athens</place>† , she had even then lost nothing but time. We may see, in <person type="Demosthenes">Demosthenes</person>, how difficult it was to awake her: she dreaded <person type="Philip">Philip</person>, not as the enemy of her liberty, but of her pleasures? . This famous city, which had withstood so many defeats, and, after having been so often destroyed, had as often risen out of her ashes, was overthrown at <place type="city">Chæronea</place>, and, at one blow, deprived of all hopes of resource. What does it avail her, that <person type="Philip">Philip</person> sends back her prisoners, if he does not return her men? It was ever after as easy to triumph over the <society type="city_state">Athenian</society> forces as it had been difficult to subdue her <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
           How was it possible for <place type="area">Carthage</place> to maintain her ground? When <person type="Hannibal">Hannibal</person>, upon his being made prætor, endeavoured to hinder the magistrates from plundering the <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, did not they complain of him to the <society type="city_state">Romans</society>? Wretches, who would fain be citizens without a city, and beholden for their riches to their very destroyers! <society type="city_state">Rome</society> soon insisted upon having three hundred of their principal citizens as hostages; she obliged them next to surrender their arms and ships; and then she declared war† . From the desperate efforts of this defenceless city, one may judge of what she might have performed in her full vigour, and assisted by <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Principle Of Aristocracy.</subheading>
        <p>
          AS <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is necessary in a popular government, it is requisite, also, under an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>. True it is, that, in the latter, it is not so absolutely requisite.
          The people, who, in respect to the nobility, are the same as the subjects with regard to a monarch, are restrained by their laws: they have, therefore, less occasion for <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> than the people in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. But how are the nobility to be restrained? They, who are to execute the laws against their colleagues, will immediately perceive they are acting against themselves. Virtue is, therefore, necessary in this body, from the very nature of the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>.
          An aristocratical government has an inherent vigour, unknown to <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. The nobles form a body, who, by their prerogative, and for their own particular interest, restrain the people; it is sufficient, that there are laws in being, to see them executed.
          But, easy as it may be for the body of the nobles to restrain the people, it is difficult to restrain themselves* . Such is the nature of this <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>, that it seems to subject the very same persons to the power of the laws, and, at the same time, to exempt them.
          Now, such a body as this can restrain itself only two ways; either by a very eminent <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which puts the nobility, in some measure, on a level with the people, and may be the means of forming a great <governments type="republic">republic</governments>; or by an inferior <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which puts them, at least, upon a level with one another; and on this their preservation depends.
          Moderation is, therefore, the very soul of this government; a moderation, I mean, founded on <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, not that which proceeds from indolence and pusillanimity.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
            <subheading>That Virtue Is Not The Principle Of A Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, policy effects great things with as little <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> as possible. Thus, in the nicest machines, art has reduced the number of movements, springs, and wheels.
            The state subsists independently of the love of our country, of the thirst of true glory, of self-denial, of the sacrifice of our dearest interests, and of all those heroic <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s which we admire in the ancients, and to us are known only by story.
            The laws supply here the place of those <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s; they are by no means wanted, and the state dispenses with them: an action, performed here in secret, is, in some measure, of no consequence.
            Though all crimes be, in their own nature, public, yet there is a distinction between crimes really public and those that are private, which are so called, because they are more injurious to individuals than to the community.
            Now, in <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, private crimes are more public; that is, they attack the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents> more than they do individuals: and, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, public crimes are more private; that is, they are more prejudicial to private people than to the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents>.
            I beg that no one will be offended with what I have been saying; my observations are founded on the unanimous testimony of historians. I am not ignorant that virtuous princes are no such very rare instances; but I venture to affirm, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, it is extremely difficult for the people to be virtuous* .
            Let us compare what the historians of all ages have asserted concerning the courts of monarchs; let us recollect the conversations and sentiments of people of all countries in respect to the wretched character of courtiers; and we shall find, that these are not airy speculations, but truths, confirmed by a sad and melancholy experience.
            Ambition in idleness, meanness mixed with pride, a desire of riches without industry, aversion to truth, flattery, perfidy, violation of engagements, contempt of civil duties, fear of the prince’s <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, hope from his weakness, but, above all, a perpetual ridicule cast upon <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, are, I think, the characteristics by which most courtiers, in all ages and countries, have been constantly distinguished. Now, it is exceeding difficult for the leading men of the nation to be knaves, and the inferior sort to be honest; for the former to be cheats, and the latter to rest satisfied with being only dupes.
            But, if there should chance to be some unlucky honest man† among the people, cardinal Richelieu, in his political testament, seems to hint that a prince should take
            care not to employ him‡ . So true is it, that <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is not the spring of this government. It is not, indeed, excluded, but it is not the spring of government.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VI.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner Virtue Is Supplied In A Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            BUT it is high time for me to have done with this subject, lest I should be suspected of writing a satire against <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> government. Far be it from me; if <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> wants one spring, it is provided with another. Honour, that is, the prejudice of every person and rank, supplieth the place of the political <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> of which I have been speaking, and is every where her representative: here it is capable of inspiring the most glorious actions, and, joined with the force of laws, may lead us to the end of government as well as <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> itself.
            Hence, in well-regulated <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, they are almost all good subjects, and very few good men; for, to be a good man† , a good intention is necessary* , and we should love our country not so much on our own account as out of regard to the community.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Principle Of Monarchy.</subheading>
        <p>
            A <governments type="monarchial">monarchical government</governments> supposeth, as we have already observed, pre-eminences and ranks, as likewise a noble descent. Now, since it is<human_behavior type="human_nature"> the nature</human_behavior> of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> to aspire to preferments and titles, it is properly placed in this government.
            <human_behavior type="human_nature">Ambition is pernicious</human_behavior> in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>; but in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> it has some good effects; <rationale type="political">it gives life to the government</rationale>, and <rationale type="philosophy">is attended with this advantage, that it is no way dangerous, because it may be continually checked</rationale>.
            It is with this kind of government as with the system of the universe, in which there <rationale type="philosophy">is a power that constantly repels all bodies from the center</rationale>, and a power of gravitation, that attracts them to it. Honour sets all the parts of the body politic in motion, and, by its very action, connects them; thus each individual advances the public good, while he only thinks of promoting his own interest.
            True it is, that, philosophically speaking, it is a false <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> which moves all the parts of the government; but even this false <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> is as useful to the public as true <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> could possibly be to private people.
            Is it not a very great point, to oblige men to perform the most difficult actions, such as require an extraordinary exertion of fortitude and resolution, without any other recompence than that of glory and applause?
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>That Honour Is Not The Principle Of Despotic Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            <characteristics type="ideals">HONOUR</characteristics> is far from being the principle of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments>: mankind being here all upon a level, <natural_law type="equality">no one person can prefer himself to another</natural_law>; and as, on the other hand, <rationale type="logical">they are all slaves, they can give themselves no sort of preference.</rationale>
            Besides, as <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> has its laws and rules; as it knows not how to submit; as it depends, in a great measure, <rationale type="philosophy">on a man’s own caprice, and not on that of another person;</rationale> it can be <governments type="nationally_governed">found only in countries </governments> in which the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents> is fixed, and where they are governed by settled laws.
            How can despotism bear with <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>? This glories in the contempt of life, and that is founded in the power of taking it away. How can <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, on the other hand, bear with despotism? The former has its fixed rules and peculiar caprices, but the latter is directed by no rule, and its own caprices are subversive of all others.
            Honour, therefore, a thing unknown in arbitrary governments, some of which have not even a proper word to express it* , is the prevailing principle in monarchies; here it gives life to the whole body politic, to the laws, and even to the <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s themselves.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IX.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Principle Of Despotic Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            AS <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is necessary in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, and, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, so fear is necessary in a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments>: with regard to <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, there is no occasion for it, and <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> would be extremely dangerous.
            Here, the immense power of the prince is devolved intirely upon those whom he is pleased to intrust with the administration. Persons, capable of setting a value upon themselves, would be likely to create disturbances. Fear must, therefore, depress their spirits, and extinguish even the least sense of ambition.
            A moderate government may, whenever it pleases, and without the least danger, relax its springs: it supports itself by the laws and by its own internal strength. But, when a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> prince ceases one single moment to lift up his arm, when he cannot instantly demolish those whom he has intrusted with the first employments† , all is over: for, as fear, the spring of this government, no longer subsists, the people are left without a protector.
            It is probably in this sense the Cadis maintained that the Grand Seignior was not obliged to keep his word or oath, when he limited thereby his authority‡ .
            It is necessary that the people should be judged by laws, and the great men by the caprice of the prince; that the lives of the lowest subjects should be safe, and the bashaw’s head ever in danger. We cannot mention these monstrous governments without horror. The <society type="state_group">Sophi of Persia</society>, dethroned, in our days, by Mahomet, the son of Miriveis, saw the <legal_documents type="constitutional">constitution</legal_documents> subverted, before this revolution, because he had been too sparing of blood* .
            History informs us, that the horrid cruelties of Domitian struck such a terror into the governors, that the people recovered themselves a little under his reign§ . Thus a torrent overflows one side of a country, and, on the other, leaves fields untouched, where the eye is refreshed by the prospect of fine meadows.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. X.</chapter>
            <subheading>Difference Of Obedience In Moderate And Despotic Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> states, the nature of government requires the most passive obedience; and, when once the prince’s will is made known, it ought infallibly to produce its effect.
            Here they have no limitations or restrictions; no mediums, terms, equivalents, or remonstrances; no change to propose: man is a creature that blindly submits to the absolute will of the sovereign.
            In a country like this, they are no more allowed to represent their apprehensions of a future danger than to impute their miscarriage to the capriciousness of fortune. Man’s portion here, like that of beasts, is instinct, compliance, and punishment.
            Little does it then avail to plead the sentiments of nature, filial respect, conjugal or parental tenderness, the laws of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, or want of health; the order is given, and that is sufficient.
            In <place type="state">Persia</place>, when the king has condemned a person, it is no longer lawful to mention his name or to intercede in his favour. Even if the prince were intoxicated, or non compos, the decree must be executed* ; otherwise he would contradict himself, and the law admits of no contradiction. This has been the way of thinking in that country in all ages: as the order, which Ahasuerus gave, to exterminate the Jews, could not be revoked, they were allowed the liberty of defending themselves.
            One thing, however, may be sometimes opposed to the prince’s will§ , namely, religion. They will abandon, nay, they will slay, a parent, if the prince so commands, but he cannot oblige them to drink wine. The laws of religion are of a superior nature, because they bind the sovereign as well as the subject. But, with respect to the law of nature, it is otherwise; the prince is no longer supposed to be a man.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> and moderate states, the power is limited by its very spring, I mean, by <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, which, like a monarch, reigns over the prince and his people. They will not alledge to their sovereign, the laws of religion; a courtier would be apprehensive of rendering himself ridiculous. But the laws of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> will be appealed to on all occasions. Hence arise the restrictions necessary to obedience: <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> is naturally subject to whims, by which the subject’s submission will be ever directed.
            Though the manner of obeying be different, in these two kinds of government, the power is the same. On which side soever the monarch turns, he inclines the scale, and is obeyed. The whole difference is, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, the prince receives instruction, at the same time that his ministers have greater abilities, and are more versed in public affairs, than the ministers of a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XI.</chapter>
            <subheading>>Reflections On The Preceding Chapters.</subheading>
        <p>
            <separation_of_powers type="generally_referenced">SUCH are the principles of the three sorts of government</separation_of_powers>: which does not imply, that, in a particular <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, they actually are, but that they ought to be, virtuous: nor does it prove, that, in a particular <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, they are actuated by <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>; or, in a particular <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, by fear; but that <rationale type="political">they ought to be directed by these principles, otherwise the government is imperfect.</rationale>
        </p>
    </book>
    
    <book>IV.
        <heading>THAT THE LAWS OF EDUCATION OUGHT TO BE RELATIVE TO THE PRINCIPLES OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Laws Of Education.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE laws of education are the first impressions we receive; and, as they prepare us for civil life, every private family ought to be governed by the plan of that great household which comprehends them all.
            If the people in general have a principle, their constituent parts, that is, the several families, will have one also. The laws of education will be therefore different in each species of government: in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, they will have honour for their object; in republics, virtue; in despotic governments, fear.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Education In Monarchies.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> the principal branch of education is not taught in colleges or academies: it commences, in some measure, at our setting out in the world; for this is the school of what we call honour, that universal preceptor, which ought every where to be our guide.
            Here it is that we constantly hear three rules or maxims; viz. that we should have a certain nobleness in our virtues, a kind of frankness in our morals, and a particular politeness in our behaviour.
            The virtues we are here taught are less what we owe to others than to ourselves; they are not so much what draws us towards society, as what distinguishes us from our fellow-citizens.
            Here the actions of men are judged, not as virtuous, but as shining; not as just, but as great; not as reasonable, but as extraordinary.
            When honour here meets with any thing noble in our actions, it is either a judge that approves them, or a sophister by whom they are excused.
            It allows of gallantry, when united with the idea of sensible affection, or with that of conquest: this is the reason why we never meet with so strict a purity of morals in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> as in <governments type="republic">republican</governments> governments.
            It allows of cunning and craft, when joined with the notion of greatness of soul, or importance of affairs; as, for instance, in politics, with whose finesses it is far from being offended.
            It does not forbid adulation, but when separate from the idea of a large fortune, and connected only with the sense of our mean condition.
            With regard to morals, I have observed, that the education of <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> ought to admit of a certain frankness and open carriage: truth, therefore, in conversation, is here a necessary point. But is it for the sake of truth? By no means. Truth is requisite only because a person habituated to veracity has an air of boldness and freedom. And, indeed, a man of this stamp seems to lay a stress only on the things themselves, not on the manner in which they are received.
            Hence it is, that, in proportion as this kind of frankness is commended, that of the common people is despised, which has nothing but truth and simplicity for its object.
            In fine, the education of <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> requires a certain politeness of behaviour. Man, a social animal, is formed to please in society; and a person that would break through
            the rules of decency, so as to shock those he conversed with, would lose the public esteem, and become incapable of doing any good.
            But politeness, generally speaking, does not derive its original from so pure a source: it rises from a desire of distinguishing ourselves. It is pride that renders us polite: we are flattered with being taken notice of for a behaviour that shews we are not of a mean condition, and that we have not been bred up with those who in all ages are considered as the scum of the people.
            Politeness, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, is naturalised at court. One man excessively great renders every body else little. Hence that regard which is paid to our fellow-subjects: hence that politeness, equally pleasing to those by whom, as to those towards whom, it is practised; because it gives people to understand that a person actually belongs, or at least deserves to belong, to the court.
            A court air consists in quitting a real for a borrowed greatness. The latter pleases the courtier more than the former. It inspires him with a certain disdainful modesty, which shews itself externally, but whose pride insensibly diminishes in proportion to its distance from the source of this greatness.
            At court we find a delicacy of taste in every thing; a delicacy arising from the constant use of the superfluities of life; from the variety, and especially the satiety, of pleasures; from the multiplicity, and even confusion, of fancies; which, if they are but agreeable, are sure of being well received.
            These are the things which properly fall within the province of education, in order to form what we call a man of honour, a man possessed of all the qualities and virtues requisite in this kind of government.
            Here it is that honour interferes with every thing, mixing even with people’s manner of thinking, and directing their very principles.
            To this whimsical honour it is owing that the virtues are only just what it pleases: it adds rules of its own invention to every thing prescribed to us: it extends or limits our duties according to its own fancy, whether they proceed from religion, politics, or morality.
            There is nothing so strongly inculcated, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, by the laws, by religion, and honour, as submission to the prince’s will: but this very honour tells us, that the prince never ought to command a dishonourable action; because this would render us incapable of serving him.
            Crillon refused to assassinate the duke of Guise, but offered to fight him. After the massacre of St. Bartholomew, Charles IX. having sent orders to the governors in the several provinces for the Hugonots to be murdered, viscount Dorte, who commanded at Bayonne, wrote thus to the king: * “Sire, among the inhabitants of this town, and your majesty’s troops, I could not find so much as one executioner: they are honest citizens, and brave soldiers. We jointly, therefore, beseech your majesty to command
            our arms and lives in things that are practicable.” This great and generous soul looked upon a base action as a thing impossible.
            There is nothing that honour more strongly recommends to the nobility, than to serve their prince in a military capacity: and indeed this is their favourite profession, because its dangers, its success, and even its miscarriages, are the road to grandeur. Yet this very law of its own making honour chooses to explain; and, in case of any affront, it requires or permits us to retire.    
            It insists also that we should be at liberty either to seek or to reject employments; a liberty which it prefers even to an ample fortune.
            Honour therefore has its supreme laws, to which education is obliged to conform.† The chief of these are, that we are permitted to set a value upon our fortune, but are absolutely forbidden to set any upon our lives.
            The second is, that, when we are raised to a post or preferment, we should never do or permit any thing which may seem to imply that we look upon ourselves as inferior to the rank we hold.
            The third is, that those things which honour forbids are more rigorously forbidden when the laws do not concur in the prohibition; and those it commands are more strongly insisted upon when they happen not to be commanded by law.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Education In A Despotic Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            AS education in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> tends to raise and ennoble the mind, in despotic governments its only aim is to debase it. Here it must necessarily be servile: even in power such an education will be an advantage, because every tyrant is at the same time a slave.
            Excessive obedience supposes ignorance in the person that obeys. The same it supposes in him that commands; for he has no occasion to deliberate, to doubt, to reason; he has only to will.
            <governments type="despotic">In despotic states each house is a separate government</governments>. As education, therefore, consists chiefly in social converse, it must be here very much limited: all it does is to strike the heart with fear, and to imprint on the understanding a very simple notion of a few principles of religion. Learning here proves dangerous, emulation fatal; and, as to virtue, Aristotle cannot think there is any one virtue belonging to slaves:* if so, education in despotic countries is confined within a very narrow compass.
            Here therefore education is in some measure needless: to give something, one must take away every thing; and begin with making a bad subject, in order to make a good slave.
            For why should education take pains in forming a good citizen, only to make him share in the public misery? If he loves his country, he will strive to relax the springs of government: if he miscarries, he will be undone: if he succeeds, he must expose himself, the prince, and his country, to ruin.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Difference Between The Effects Of Ancient And Modern Education.</subheading>
        <p>
            MOST of the ancients lived under governments that had virtue for their principle; and, when this was in full vigour, they performed actions unusual in our times, and at which our narrow minds are astonished.
            Another advantage their education had over ours; it never was effaced by contrary impressions. Epaminondas, the last year of his life, said, heard, beheld, and performed, the very same things as at the age in which he received the first principles of his education.
            In our days we receive three different or contrary educations; namely, of our parents, of our masters, and of the world. What we learn in the latter effaces all the ideas of the former. This in some measure arises from the contrast we experience between our religious and worldly engagements; a thing unknown to the ancients.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Education In A Republican Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            IT is in a <governments type="republic">republican government</governments> that the whole power of education is required. The fear of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments naturally rises of itself amidst threats and punishments: the honour of <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> is favoured by the passions, and favours them in its turn: but virtue is a self-renunciation, which is ever arduous and painful.
            This virtue may be defined the love of the laws and of our country. As such love requires a constant preference of public to private interest, it is the source of all private virtues; for they are nothing more than this very preference itself.
            This love is peculiar to democracies. In these alone the government is intrusted to private citizens. Now, government is like every thing else: to preserve it, we must love it.
            Has it ever been heard that kings were not fond of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, or that despotic princes hated arbitrary power?
            Every thing, therefore, depends on establishing this love in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>; and to inspire it ought to be the principal business of education: but the surest way of instilling it into children is for parents to set them an example.
            People have it generally in their power to communicate their ideas to their children; but they are still better able to transfuse their passions.
            If it happens otherwise, it is because the impressions made at home are effaced by those they have received abroad.
            It is not the young people that degenerate: they are not spoilt till those of maturer age are already sunk into corruption.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VI.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Some Institutions Among The Greeks.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE ancient Greeks, convinced of the necessity that people who live under a popular government should be trained up to virtue, made very singular institutions in order to inspire it. Upon seeing, in the life of Lycurgus, the laws that legislator gave to the Lacedæmonians, I imagine I am reading the history of the Sevarambes. The laws of Crete were the model of those of Sparta; and those of Plato reformed them.
            Let us reflect here a little on the extensive genius with which those legislators must have been endowed, to perceive that, by striking at received customs, and by confounding all manner of virtues, they should display their wisdom to the universe. Lycurgus, by blending theft with the spirit of justice, the hardest servitude with excess of liberty, the most rigid sentiments with the greatest moderation, gave stability to his city. He seemed to deprive her of all resources, such as arts, commerce, money, walls: ambition prevailed among the citizens, without hopes or improving their fortune: they had natural sentiments without the tie of a son, husband, or father; and chastity was stript even of modesty and shame. This was the road that led Sparta to grandeur and glory; and so infallible were these institutions, that it signified nothing to gain a victory over that <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, without subverting her polity.*
            By these laws Crete and Laconia were governed. Sparta was the last that fell a prey to the Macedonians, and Crete to the Romans.† The Samnites had the same institutions, which furnished those very Romans with the subject of four and twenty triumphs.?
            A character so extraordinary in the institutions of Greece has shewn itself lately in the dregs and corruption of modern times.‡ A very honest legislator has formed a people, to whom probity seems as natural as bravery to the Spartans. Mr. Penn is a real Lycurgus; and, though the former made peace his principal aim, as the latter did war, yet they resemble one another in the singular way of living to which they reduced their people, in the ascendant they had over free men, in the prejudices they overcame, and in the passions which they subdued.
            Another example we have from Paraguay. This has been the subject of an invidious charge against a society that considers the pleasure of commanding as the only happiness in life: but it will be ever a glorious undertaking to render government subservient to human happiness.§
            It is glorious indeed for this society to have been the first in pointing out to those countries the idea of religion joined with that of humanity. By repairing the devastations of the Spaniards, she has begun to heal one of the most dangerous wounds that the human species ever received.
            An exquisite sensibility to whatever she distinguishes by the name of honour, joined to her zeal for a religion which is far more humbling in respect to those who receive than to those who preach its doctrines, has set her upon vast undertakings, which she has accomplished with success. She has drawn wild people from their woods, secured them a maintenance, and clothed their nakedness; and, had she only, by this step, improved the industry of mankind, it would have been sufficient to eternize her fame.
            They, who shall attempt hereafter to introduce the like institutions, must establish the community of goods, as prescribed in Plato’s Republic; that high respect he required for the gods; that separation from strangers, for the preservation of morals; and an extensive commerce, carried on by the community, and not by private citizens. They must give our arts without our luxury, and our wants without our desires.
            They must prescribe money, the effect of which is to swell people’s fortunes beyond the bounds prescribed by nature; to learn to preserve for no purpose what has been idly hoarded up; to multiply without end our desires; and to supply the sterility of nature, of whom we have received very scanty means of inflaming our passions and of corrupting each other.
            “The Epidamnians† , perceiving their morals depraved by conversing with barbarians, chose a magistrate for making all contracts and sales, in the name and behalf of the city.” Commerce then does not corrupt the constitution, and the constitution does not deprive the society of the advantages of commerce.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VII.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Case These Singular Institutions May Be Of Service.</subheading>
        <p>
            INSTITUTIONS of this kind may be proper in <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, because they have virtue for their principle: but, to excite men to honour, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, or to imprint fear, in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, less pains are necessary.
            Besides, they cannot take place but in a small state* , in which there is a possibility of a general education, and of training up the body of the people like a single family.
            The laws of Minos, of Lycurgus, and of Plato, suppose a particular attention and care which the citizens ought to have over one another’s conduct. But an attention of this kind cannot be expected in the confusion and multitude of affairs in which a large nation is intangled.
            In institutions of this kind, money, as we have above observed, must be banished. But, in great societies, the multiplicity, variety, embarrassment, and importance, of affairs, as well as the facility of purchasing, and the slowness of exchange, require a common measure. In order to extend or support our power, we must be possessed of the means to which, by the unanimous consent of mankind, this power is annexed.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Explication Of A Paradox Of The Ancients, In Respect To Manners.</subheading>
        <p>
            THAT judicious writer, Polybius, informs us, that music was necessary to soften the manners of the Arcadians, who lived in a cold gloomy country; that the inhabitants of Cynete, who slighted music, were the cruellest of all the Greeks, and that no other town was so immersed in luxury and debauch. Plato is not afraid to affirm, that there is no possibility of making a change in music without altering the frame of government. Aristotle, who seems to have written his politics only in order to contradict Plato, agrees with him, notwithstanding, in regard to the power and influence of music over the manners of the people. This was also the opinion of Theophrastus, of Plutarch§ , and of all the ancients; an opinion grounded on mature reflection; being one of the principles of their polity* . Thus it was they enacted laws, and thus they required that cities should be governed.
            This, I fancy, must be explained in the following manner. It is observable, that, in the cities of Greece, especially those whose principal object was war, all lucrative arts and professions were considered as unworthy of a freeman. “Most arts (says Xenophon‡ ) corrupt and enervate the bodies of those that exercise them; they oblige them to sit under a shade or near the fire. They can find no leisure either for their friends or for the republic.” It was only by the corruption of some democracies that artisans became freemen. This we learn from Aristotle? , who maintains, that a well- regulated <governments type="republic">republic</governments> will never give them the right and freedom of the city† .
            Agriculture was, likewise, a servile profession, and generally practised by the inhabitants of conquered countries; such as the Helotes, among the Lacedæmonians; the Periecians, among the Cretans; the Penestes, among the Thessalians; and other conquered¶ people in other <governments type="republic">republics</governments>.
            In fine, every kind of low commerce* was infamous, among the Greeks, as it obliged a citizen to serve and wait on a slave, on a lodger, or a stranger. This was a notion that clashed with the spirit of Greek liberty; hence Plato§ , in his laws, orders a citizen to be punished if he attempted to concern himself with trade.
            Thus, in the <governments type="republic">Greek republics</governments>, the magistrates were extremely embarrassed. They would not have the citizens apply themselves to trade, to agriculture, or to the arts, and yet they would not have them idle?? . They found, therefore, employment for them in gymnic and military exercises; and none else were allowed by their institution‡ . Hence the Greeks must be considered as a society of wrestlers and boxers. Now, these exercises having a natural tendency to render people hardy and fierce, there was a necessity for tempering them with others that might soften their manners* . For this purpose, music, which influences the mind by means of the corporeal organs, was extremely proper. It is a kind of medium between manly
            exercises, which harden the body, and speculative sciences, which are apt to render us unsociable and sour. It cannot be said that music inspired virtue, for this would be inconceivable; but it prevented the effects of a savage institution, and enabled the soul to have such a share in the education as it could never have had without the assistance of harmony.
            Let us suppose, among ourselves, a society of men, so passionately fond of hunting as to make it their sole employment: they would, doubtless, contract thereby a kind of rusticity and fierceness: but, if they happen to imbibe a taste for music, we should quickly perceive a sensible difference in their customs and manners. In short, the exercises used by the Greeks could raise only one kind of passions, viz. fierceness, indignation, and cruelty: but music excites all these, and is, likewise, able to inspire the soul with a sense of pity, lenity, tenderness, and love. Our moral writers, who declaim so vehemently against the stage, sufficiently demonstrate the power of music over the mind.
            If the society abovementioned were to have no other music than that of drums and the sound of the trumpet, would it not be more difficult to accomplish this end than by the more melting tones of softer harmony? The ancients were, therefore, in the right, when, under particular circumstances, they preferred one mode to another, in regard to manners.
            But some will ask, why should music be pitched upon preferable to any other entertainment? It is because, of all sensible pleasures, there is none that less corrupts the soul. We blush to read, in Plutarch¶ , that the Thebans, in order to soften the manners of their youth, authorised, by law, a passion which ought to be proscribed by all nations.
        </p>
    </book>
    
    <book>BOOK V.
        <heading>THAT THE LAWS, GIVEN BY THE LEGISLATOR, OUGHT TO BE RELATIVE TO THE PRINCIPLE OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
            <subheading>Idea Of This Book.</subheading>
        <p>
            THAT the laws of education ought to be relative to the principle of each government has been shewn in the preceding book. Now, the same may be said of those which the legislator gives to the whole society. The relation of laws to this principle strengthens the several springs of government; and this principle derives from thence, in its turn, a new degree of vigour. And thus it is, in mechanics, that action is always followed by re-action.
            Our design is, to examine this relation in each government, beginning with the republican state, whose principle is virtue.
        </p>
        <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>What Is Meant By Virtue In A Political State.</subheading>
        <p>
            VIRTUE in a republic is a most simple thing; it is a love of the republic; it is a sensation, and not a consequence of acquired knowledge; a sensation that may be felt by the meanest as well as by the highest person in the state. When the common people adopt good maxims, they adhere to them steadier than those we call gentlemen. It is very rare that corruption commences with the former: nay, they frequently derive from their imperfect light a stronger attachment to the established laws and customs.
            The love of our country is conducive to a purity of morals, and the latter is again conducive to the former. The less we are able to satisfy our private passions, the more we abandon ourselves to those of a general nature. How comes it that monks are so fond of their order? It is owing to the very cause that renders the order insupportable. Their rule debars them of all those things by which the ordinary passions are fed; there remains, therefore, only this passion for the very rule that torments them: the more austere it is, that is, the more it curbs their inclinations, the more force it gives to the only passion left them.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>What Is Meant By A Love Of The Republic, In A Democracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            <rationale type="political">A love of the republic, in a democracy, is a love of the democracy;</rationale> as the latter is that of equality.
            A love of the democracy is, likewise, that of frugality. Since every individual ought here to enjoy the same happiness and the same advantages, they should, consequently, taste the same pleasures and form the same hopes; which cannot be expected but from a general frugality.
            The love of equality, in a democracy, limits ambition to the sole desire, to the sole happiness, of doing greater services to our country than the rest of our fellow-citizens. They cannot all render her equal services, but they all ought to serve her with equal alacrity. At our coming into the world, we contract an immense debt to our country, which we can never discharge.
            Hence distinctions here arise from the principle of equality, even when it seems to be removed by signal services or superior abilities.
            The love of frugality limits the desire of having, to the study of procuring, necessaries to our family, and superfluities to our country. Riches give a power which a citizen cannot use for himself, for then he would be no longer equal. They likewise procure pleasures which he ought not to enjoy, because these would be also repugnant to the equality.
            Thus well-regulated democracies, by establishing domestic frugality, made way, at the same time, for public expences; as was the case at Rome and Athens, when magnificence and profusion arose from the very fund of frugality. And, as religion commands us to have pure and unspotted hands, when we make our offerings to the gods, the laws required a frugality of life, to enable them to be liberal to our country.
            The good sense and happiness of individuals depend greatly on the mediocrity of their abilities and fortunes. Therefore, as a republic, where the laws have placed many in a middling station, is composed of wise men, it will be wisely governed; as it is composed of happy men, it will be extremely happy.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner The Love Of Equality And Frugality Is Inspired.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE love of equality and of a frugal œconomy is greatly excited by equality and frugality themselves, in societies, where both these virtues are established by law.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> and <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, no body aims at equality; this does not so much as enter their thoughts; they all aspire to superiority. People of the very lowest condition desire to emerge from their obscurity, only to lord it over their fellow- subjects.
            It is the same with respect to frugality. To love it, we must practise and enjoy it. It is not those who are enervated with pleasure that are fond of a frugal life: were this natural and common, Alcibiades would never have been the admiration of the universe. Neither is it those who envy or admire the luxury of the great: people, that have present to their view none but rich men, or men miserable like themselves, detest their wretched condition, without loving or knowing the real term or point of misery.
            A true maxim it is, therefore, that, in order to love equality and frugality in a republic, these virtues must have been previously established by law.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner The Laws Establish Equality In A Democracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            SOME ancient legislators, as Lycurgus and Romulus, made an equal division of lands. A settlement of this kind can never take place but upon the foundation of a new republic, or when the old one is so corrupt, and the minds of the people are so disposed, that the poor think themselves obliged to demand, and the rich obliged to consent to, a remedy of this nature.
            If the legislator, in making a division of this kind, does not enact laws, at the same time, to support it, he forms only a temporary constitution; inequality will break in where the laws have not precluded it, and the republic will be utterly undone.
            Hence, for the preservation of this equality, it is absolutely necessary there should be some regulation in respect to womens dowries, donations, successions, testamentary settlements, and all other forms of contracting. For, were it once allowed to dispose of our property to whom and how we pleased, the will of each individual would disturb the order of the fundamental law.
            <person type="Solon">Solon</person>, by permitting the Athenians, upon failure of issue* , to leave their estates to whom they pleased, acted contrary to the ancient laws, by which the estates were ordered to continue in the family of the testator† , and even contrary to his own laws; for, by abolishing debts, he had aimed at equality.
            The law, which prohibited people’s having two inheritances§ , was extremely well adapted for a democracy: it derived its origin from the equal distribution of lands and portions made to each citizen. The law would not permit a single man to possess more than a single portion.
            From the same source arose those laws by which the next relation was ordered to marry the heiress. This law was given to the Jews after the like distribution. Plato¶ , who grounds his laws on this division, made the same regulation which had been received as a law by the Athenians.
            At Athens, there was a law, whose spirit, in my opinion, has not been hitherto rightly understood. It was lawful to marry a sister only by the father’s side, but it was not permitted to espouse a sister by the same venter* . This custom was originally owing to republics, whose spirit would not permit that two portions of land, and consequently two inheritances, should devolve on the same person. A man, who married his sister only by the father’s side, could inherit but one estate, namely, that of his father; but, by espousing his sister by the same venter, it might happen, that his sister’s father, having no male issue, might leave her his estate, and, consequently, the brother, who married her, might be possessed of two.
            Little will it avail to object what Philo says‡ , that, although the Athenians were allowed to marry a sister by the father’s side, and not by the mother’s, yet the contrary practice prevailed among the Lacedæmonians, who were permitted to espouse a sister by the mother’s side, and not by the father’s. For I find, in Strabo† , that, at Sparta, whenever a woman was married to her brother, she had half his portion for her dowry. Plain it is, that this second law was made in order to prevent the bad consequences of the former. That the estate belonging to the sister’s family might not devolve on the brother’s, they gave half the brother’s estate to the sister for her dowry.
            Seneca,? speaking of Silanus, who had married his sister, says, that the permission was limited at Athens, but general at Alexandria. In a monarchical government there was very little concern about any such thing as a division of estates.
            Excellent was that law, which, in order to maintain this division of lands in a democracy, ordained, that a father, who had several children, should pitch upon one of them to inherit his portion,§ and leave the others to be adopted, to the end that the number of citizens might always be kept upon an equality with that of the divisions.
            Phaleas of Chalcedon‡ contrived a very extraordinary method of rendering all fortunes equal, in a republic where there was the greatest inequality. This was, that the rich should give fortunes with their daughters to the poor, but receive none themselves; and that the poor should receive money for their daughters, instead of giving them fortunes. But I do not remember that a regulation of this kind ever took place in any republic. It lays the citizens under such hard and oppressive conditions, as would make them detest the very equality which they designed to establish. It is proper sometimes that the laws should not seem to tend so directly to the end they propose.
            Though real equality be the very soul of a democracy, it is so difficult to establish, that an extreme exactness in this respect would not be always convenient. Sufficient it is to establish a census,* which should reduce or fix the differences to a certain point: it is afterwards the business of particular laws to level, as it were, the inequalities, by the duties laid upon the rich, and by the ease afforded to the poor. It is moderate riches alone that can give or suffer this sort of compensations; for, as to men of over- grown estates, every thing which does not contribute to advance their power and honour is considered by them as an injury.
            All inequality in democracies ought to be derived from the nature of the government, and even from the principle of equality. For example, it may be apprehended that people, who are obliged to live by their labour, would be too much impoverished by a public employment, or neglect the duties attending it; that artisans would grow insolent; and that too great a number of freemen would overpower the ancient citizens. In this case the equality† in a democracy may be suppressed, for the good of the state. But this is only an apparent equality: for a man ruined by a public employment would be in a worse condition than his fellow-citizens; and this same man, being obliged to neglect his duty, would reduce the rest to a worse condition than himself; and so on.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VI.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner The Laws Ought To Maintain Frugality In A Democracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            IT is not sufficient, in a well-regulated democracy, that the divisions of land be equal; they ought also to be small, as was customary among the Romans. “God forbid,” said Curius to his soldiers,‡ “that a citizen should look upon that as a small piece of land which is sufficient to maintain him.”
            As equality of fortunes supports frugality, so the latter maintains the former. These things, though in themselves different, are of such a nature as to be unable to subsist separately: they reciprocally act upon each other: if one withdraws itself from a democracy, the other surely follows it.
            True it is, that, when a democracy is founded in commerce, private people may acquire vast riches without a corruption of morals. This is because the spirit of commerce is naturally attended with that of frugality, œconomy, moderation, labour, prudence, tranquility, order, and rule. So long as this spirit subsists, the riches it produces have no bad effect. The mischief is when excessive wealth destroys the spirit of commerce: then it is that the inconveniences of inequality begin to be felt.
            In order to support this spirit, commerce should be carried on by the principal citizens: this should be their sole aim and study; this the chief object of the laws: and these very laws, by dividing the estates of individuals in proportion to the increase of commerce, should set every poor citizen so far at his ease, as to be able to work like the rest; and every wealthy citizen in such a mediocrity, as to be obliged to take some pains either in preserving or acquiring a fortune.
            It is an excellent law, in a trading republic, to make an equal division of the paternal estate among the children. The consequence of this is, that, how great soever a fortune the father has made, his children, being not so rich as he, are induced to avoid luxury, and to work as he had done. I speak here only of trading republics; for, as to those that have no commerce, the legislator must pursue quite different measures.*
            In Greece there were two sorts of republics; the one military, like Sparta; the other commercial, as Athens. In the former, the citizens were obliged to be idle; in the latter, endeavours were used to inspire them with the love of industry and labour. <person type="Solon">Solon</person> made idleness a crime, and insisted that each citizen should give an account of his manner of getting a livelihood. And indeed, in a well-regulated democracy, where people’s expences should extend only to what is necessary, every one ought to have it; for how should their wants be otherwise supplied?
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Other Methods Of Favouring The Principle Of Democracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            AN equal division of lands cannot be established in all democracies. There are some circumstances in which a regulation of this nature would be impracticable, dangerous, and even subversive of the constitution. We are not always obliged to proceed to extremes. If it appears that this division of lands, which was designed to preserve the people’s morals, does not suit with the democracy, recourse must be had to other methods.
            If a permanent body be established, to serve as a rule and pattern of manners; a senate, to which years, virtue, gravity, and eminent services, procure admittance; the senators, by being exposed to public view like the statues of the gods, must naturally inspire every family with sentiments of virtue.
            Above all, this senate must steadily adhere to the ancient institutions, and mind that the people and the magistrates never swerve from them.
            The preservation of the ancient customs is a very considerable point in respect to manners. Since a corrupt people seldom perform any memorable actions, seldom establish societies, build cities, or enact laws: on the contrary, since most institutions are derived from people whose manners are plain and simple, to keep up the ancient custom is the way to preserve the original purity of morals.
            Besides, if, by some revolution, the state has happened to assume a new form, this seldom can be effected without infinite pains and labour, and hardly ever by idle and debauched persons. Even those who had been the instruments of the revolution were desirous it should be relished; which is difficult to compass without good laws. Hence it is that ancient institutions generally tend to reform the people’s manners, and those of modern date to corrupt them. In the course of a long administration the descent to vice is insensible; but there is no reascending to virtue without making the most generous efforts.
            It has been questioned, whether the members of the senate we are speaking of ought to be for life, or only chosen for a time. Doubtless they ought to be for life, as was the custom at Rome,* at Sparta,† and even at Athens: for we must not confound the senate at Athens, which was a body that changed every three months, with the Areopagus, whose members, as standing patterns, were established for life.
            Let this be therefore a general maxim; that, in a senate designed to be a rule and the depositary, as it were, of manners, the members ought to be chosen for life; in a senate intended for the administration of affairs the members may be changed.
            The spirit, says Aristotle, waxes old, as well as the body. This reflection holds good only in regard to a single magistrate, but cannot be applied to a senatorian assembly.
            At Athens, beside the Areopagus, there were guardians of the public morals, as well as of the laws.‡ At Sparta all the old men were censors. At Rome the censorship was committed to two particular magistrates. As the senate watched over the people, the censors were to have an eye over the people and the senate. Their office was to reform the corruptions of the republic, to stigmatize indolence, to censure neglects, and to correct mistakes: as to flagrant crimes, these were left to the punishment of the laws.
            That Roman law, which required the accusations in cases of adultery to be public, was admirably well calculated for preserving the purity of morals; it intimidated married women, as well as those who were to watch over their conduct.
            Nothing contributes more to the preservation of morals than an extreme subordination of the young to the old. Thus they are both restrained, the former by their respect for those of advanced <eligibility type="age">age</eligibility>, and the latter by their regard for themselves.
            Nothing gives a greater force to the laws than a perfect subordination between the citizens and the magistrate. “The great difference which Lycurgus established between Sparta and the other cities (says Xenophon* ) consists chiefly in the obedience the citizens shew to the laws: they run when the magistrate calls them. But, at Athens, a rich man would be highly displeased to be thought dependent on the magistrate.”
            Paternal authority is likewise of great use towards the preservation of morals. We have already observed, that, in a republic, there is not so coercive a force as in other governments. The laws must therefore endeavour to supply this defect by some means or other; and this is done by paternal authority.
            Fathers, at Rome, had the power of life and death over their children.† At Sparta every father had a right to correct another man’s child.
            Paternal authority ended, at Rome, together with the republic. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, where such a purity of morals is not required, they are controuled by no other authority than that of the magistrates.
            The Roman laws, which accustomed young people to dependence, established a long minority. Perhaps we are mistaken in conforming to this custom: there is no necessity for so much constraint in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>.
            This very subordination in a republic might make it necessary for the father to continue in the possession of his children’s fortune during life, as was the custom at Rome. But this is not agreeable to the spirit of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner The Laws Ought To Be Relative To The Principle Of Government In An Aristocracy.</subheading>
        <p>
            IF the people are virtuous in an aristocracy, they enjoy very near the same happiness as in a popular government, and the state grows powerful. But, as a great share of virtue is very rare where mens fortunes are so unequal, the laws must tend as much as possible to infuse a spirit of moderation, and endeavour to re-establish that equality which was necessarily removed by the constitution.
            The spirit of moderation is what we call virtue in an aristocracy; it supplies the place of the spirit of equality in a popular state.
            As the pomp and splendor, with which kings are surrounded, form a part of their power, so modesty and simplicity of manners constitute the strength of an aristocratic nobility* . When they affect no distinction, when they mix with the people, dress like them, and with them share all their pleasures, the people are apt to forget their subjection and weakness.
            Every government has its nature and principle. An aristocracy must not, therefore, assume the nature and principle of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>; which would be the case, were the nobles to be invested with personal privileges distinct from those of their body. Privileges ought to be for the senate, and simple respect for the senators.
            In aristocratical governments, there are two principal sources of disorder: excessive inequality between the governors and the governed; and the same inequality between the different members of the body that governs. From these two inequalities hatreds and jealousies arise, which the laws ought ever to prevent or repress.
            The first inequality is, chiefly, when the privileges of the nobility are honourable only as they are ignominious to the people. Such was the law, at Rome, by which the patricians were forbidden to marry plebeians* ; a law that had no other effect than to render the patricians, on the one side, more haughty, and, on the other, more odious. The reader may see what advantages the tribunes derived from thence in their harangues.
            This inequality occurs, likewise, when the condition of the citizens differs with regard to taxes: which may happen four different ways; when the nobles assume the privilege of paying none; when they commit frauds to exempt themselves† ; when they engross the public money, under pretence of rewards or appointments for their respective employments; in fine, when they render the common people tributary, and divide among their own body the profits arising from the several subsidies. This last case is very rare; an aristocracy so instituted would be the most intolerable of all governments.
            While Rome inclined towards an aristocracy, she avoided all these inconveniences. The magistrates never received any emoluments from their office: the chief men of the republic were taxed like the rest, nay, heavier; and sometimes the taxes fell upon them alone. In fine, far from sharing among themselves the revenues of the state, all they could draw from the public treasure, and all the wealth that fortune flung into their laps, they bestowed freely on the people, to be excused from accepting public honours? .
            It is a fundamental maxim, that largesses are pernicious to the people in a democracy, but salutary in an aristocratical government. The former make them forget they are citizens, the latter bring them to a sense of it.
            If the revenues of the state are not distributed amongst the people, they must be convinced, at least, of their being well administered: to feast their eyes with the public treasure is, with them, the same thing almost as enjoying it. The golden chain displayed at Venice, the riches exhibited at Rome in public triumphs, the treasures preserved in the temple of Saturn, were, in reality, the wealth of the people.
            It is a very essential point, in an aristocracy, that the nobles themselves should not levy the taxes. The first order of the state, in Rome, never concerned themselves with it; the levying of taxes was committed to the second; and even this, in process of time, was attended with great inconveniences. In an aristocracy of this kind, where the nobles levied the taxes, the private people would be all at the discretion of persons in public employments, and there would be no such thing as a superior tribunal to check their power. The members, appointed to remove the abuses, would rather enjoy them: the nobles would be like the princes of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, who confiscate whatever estates they please.
            Soon would the profits, hence arising, be considered as a patrimony, which avarice would enlarge at pleasure. The farms would be lowered, and the public revenues reduced to nothing. This is the reason that some governments, without having ever received any remarkable shock, have dwindled away to such a degree, as not only their neighbours, but even their own subjects, have been surprized at it.
            The laws should likewise forbid the nobles all kind of commerce: merchants of such unbounded credit would monopolize all to themselves. Commerce is a profession of people who are upon an equality; hence, among <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> states, the most miserable are those in which the prince applies himself to trade.
            The laws of Venice debar‡ the nobles from commerce, by which they might, even innocently, acquire exorbitant wealth.
            The laws ought to employ the most effectual means for making the nobles do justice to the people. If they have not established a tribune, they ought to be a tribune themselves.
            Every sort of asylum, in opposition to the execution of the laws, destroys aristocracy, and is soon succeeded by tyranny.
            They ought always to mortify the lust of dominion. There should be either a temporary or perpetual magistrate to keep the nobles in awe; as the Ephori at Sparta, and the State-Inquistors at Venice, magistrates subject to no formalities. This sort of government stands in need of the strongest springs: thus a mouth of stone§ is open to every informer at Venice; a mouth to which one would be apt to give the appellation of tyranny.
            These arbitrary magistrates in an aristocracy bear some analogy to the censorship in democracies, which, of its own nature, is equally independent. And, indeed, the censors ought to be subject to no enquiry in relation to their conduct during their office; they should meet with a thorough confidence, and never be discouraged. In this respect, the practice of the Romans deserved admiration; magistrates of all denominations were accountable for their administration¶ , except the censors* .
            There are two very pernicious things in an aristocracy; excess either of poverty or of wealth in the nobility. To prevent their poverty, it is necessary, above all things, to oblige them to pay their debts in time. To moderate the excess of wealth, prudent and gradual regulations should be made; but no confiscations, no agrarian laws, no expunging of debts; these are productive of infinite mischief.
            The laws ought to abolish the right of primogeniture among the nobles† , to the end, that, by a continual division of the inheritances, their fortunes may be always upon a level.
            There should be no substitutions, no powers of redemption, no rights of majorasgo, or adoption. The contrivances, for perpetuating the grandeur of families, in monarchical governments, ought never to be employed in aristocracies‡ .
            When the laws have compassed the equality of families, the next thing is to preserve a proper harmony and union amongst them. The quarrels of the nobility ought to be quickly decided; otherwise the contests of individuals become those of families. Arbiters may terminate, or even prevent the rise of, disputes.
            In fine, the laws must not favour the distinctions raised by vanity among families, under pretence that they are more noble or ancient than others: pretences of this nature ought to be ranked among the weaknesses of private persons.
            We have only to cast an eye on Sparta; there we may see how the Ephori contrived to check the foibles of the kings, as well as those of the nobility and common people.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IX.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Manner The Laws Are Relative To Their Principle In Monarchies.</subheading>
        <p>
            AS honour is the principle of a monarchical government, the laws ought to be relative to this principle.
            They should endeavour to support the nobility; in respect to whom, honour may be, in some measure, deemed both child and parent.
            They should render the nobility hereditary; not as a boundary between the power of the prince and the weakness of the people, but as the link which connects them both.
            In this government, substitutions, which preserve the estates of families undivided, are extremely useful, though in others not so proper.
            Here the power of redemption is of service, as it restores to noble families the lands that had been alienated by the prodigality of a parent.
            The lands of the nobility ought to have privileges as well as their persons. The monarch’s dignity is inseparable from that of his kingdom, and the dignity of the nobleman from that of his fief.
            All these privileges must be particular to the nobility and incommunicable to the people, unless we intend to act contrary to the principle of government, and to diminish the power of the nobles together with that of the people.
            Substitutions are a restraint to commerce; the power of redemption produces an infinite number of processes; every estate in land, that is sold throughout the kingdom, is, in some measure, without an owner for the space of a year. Privileges annexed to fiefs give a power very burthensome to those governments which tolerate them. These are the inconveniences of nobility; inconveniences, however, that vanish when confronted with its general utility. But, when these privileges are communicated to the people, every principle of government is wantonly violated.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, a person may leave the bulk of his estate to one of his children; a permission improper in any other government.
            The laws ought to favour all kind of commerce? consistent with the constitution, to the end that the subjects may, without ruining themselves, be able to satisfy the continual cravings of the prince and his court.
            They should establish some regulation, that the manner of collecting the taxes may not be more burthensome than the taxes themselves.
            The weight of duties produces labour, labour weariness, and weariness the spirit of indolence.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. X.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Expedition Peculiar To The Executive Power In Monarchies.</subheading>
        <p>
            GREAT is the advantage which a monarchical government has over a republic. As the state is conducted by a single person, the executive power is thereby enabled to act with greater expedition: but, as this expedition may degenerate into rapidity, the laws should use some contrivance to slacken it: they ought not only to favour the nature of each constitution, but likewise to remedy the abuses that might result from this very nature.
            Cardinal Richelieu§ advises monarchs to permit no such things as societies or communities that raise difficulties upon every trifle. If this man’s heart had not been bewitched with the love of despotic power, still these arbitrary notions would have filled his head.
            The bodies, intrusted with the depositum of the laws, are never more obedient than when they proceed slowly, and use that reflection in the prince’s affairs which can scarcely be expected from the ignorance of a court, or from the precipitation of its councils¶ .
            What would have become of the finest <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> in the world, if the magistrates, by their delays, their complaints, and entreaties, had not checked the rapidity even of their princes virtues, when these monarchs, consulting only the generous impulse of their minds, would fain have given a boundless reward to services performed with an unlimited courage and fidelity?
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XI.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Excellence Of A Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            MONARCHY has a great advantage over a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government. As it naturally requires there should be several orders or ranks of subjects, the state is more permanent, the constitution more steady, and the person of him who governs more secure.
            Cicero* is of opinion, that the establishing of the tribunes preserved the republic. “And, indeed, (says he,) the violence of a headless people is more terrible. A chief, or head, is sensible that the affair depends upon himself, and therefore he thinks; but the people, in their impetuosity, are ignorant of the danger into which they hurry themselves.” This reflection may be applied to a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, which is a people without tribunes, and to a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, where the people have some sort of tribunes.
            Accordingly, it is observable, that, in the commotions of a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, the people, hurried away by their passions, are apt to push things as far as they can go. The disorders they commit are all extreme; whereas, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, matters are seldom carried to excess. The chiefs are apprehensive on their own account; they are afraid of being abandoned; and the intermediate dependent powers† do not choose that the populace should have too much the upper hand. It rarely happens that the states of the kingdom are entirely corrupted: the prince adheres to these; and the seditious, who have neither will nor hopes to subvert the government, have neither power nor will to dethrone the prince.
            In these circumstances, men of prudence and authority interfere; moderate measures are first proposed, then complied with, and things at length are redressed; the laws resume their vigour, and command submission.
            Thus all our histories are full of civil wars without revolutions, while the histories of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments abound with revolutions without civil wars.
            The writers of the history of the civil wars of some countries, even those who fomented them, sufficiently demonstrate the little foundation princes have to suspect the authority with which they invest particular bodies of men; since, even under the unhappy circumstance of their errors, they sighed only after the laws and their duty, and restrained, more than they were capable of inflaming, the impetuosity of the revolted? .
            Cardinal Richelieu, reflecting perhaps that he had too much reduced the states of the kingdom, has recourse to the virtues of the prince and of his ministers for the support‡ of government: but he requires so many things, that indeed there is none but an angel
            capable of such attention, such resolution, and knowledge; and scarce can we flatter ourselves ever to see such a prince and ministers, no not while <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> subsists.
            As people, who live under a good government, are happier than those who, without rule or leaders, wander about the forests; so monarchs, who live under the fundamental laws of their country, are far happier than despotic princes, who have nothing to regulate either their own passions or those of their subjects.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XII.</chapter>
        <subheading>The Same Subject Continued.</subheading>
        <p>
            LET us not look for magnanimity in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments. The prince cannot impart a greatness which he has not himself: with him there is no such thing as glory.
            It is in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> we behold the subjects encircling the throne, and cheered by the irradiancy of the sovereign: there it is that each person, filling, as it were, a larger space, is capable of exercising those virtues which adorn the soul, not with independence, but with true dignity and greatness.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>An Idea Of Despotic Power.</subheading>
        <p>
            WHEN the savages of Louisiana are desirous of fruit, they cut the tree to the root, and
            gather the fruit.* This is an emblem of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIV.</chapter>
        <subheading>In What Manner The Laws Are Relative To The Principles Of Despotic Government.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE principle of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government is fear: but a timid, ignorant, and faint-spirited people have no occasion for a great number of laws.
            Every thing ought to depend here on two or three ideas: hence there is no necessity that any new notions should be added. When we want to break a horse, we take care not to let him change his master, his lesson, or his pace. Thus an impression is made on his brain by two or three motions, and no more.
            If a prince is shut up in a seraglio, he cannot leave his voluptuous abode without alarming those who keep him confined. They will not bear that his person and power should pass into other hands. He seldom, therefore, wages war in person, and hardly ventures to intrust the command to his generals.
            A prince of this stamp, unaccustomed to resistance in his palace, is enraged to see his will opposed by armed force: hence he is generally governed by wrath or vengeance. Besides, he can have no notion of true glory. War, therefore, is carried on, under such a government, in its full natural fury, and less extent is given to the law of nations than in other states.
            Such a prince has so many imperfections, that they are afraid to expose his natural stupidity to public view. He is concealed in his palace, and the people are ignorant of his situation. It is lucky for him that the inhabitants of those countries need only the name of a prince to govern them.
            When Charles XII. was at Bender, he met with some opposition from the senate of Sweden: upon which he wrote word home that he would send one of his boots to command them. This boot would have governed like a despotic prince.
            If the prince is a prisoner, he is supposed to be dead, and another mounts the throne. The treaties made by the prisoner are void; his successor will not ratify them. And, indeed, (as he is the law, the state, and the prince,) when he is no longer a prince, he is nothing: were he not, therefore, deemed to be deceased, the state would be subverted.
            One thing which chiefly determined the Turks to conclude a separate peace with Peter I. was the Muscovites telling the vizir, that, in Sweden, another prince had been set upon the throne.†
            The preservation of the state is only the preservation of the prince, or rather of the palace where he is confined. Whatever does not directly menace this palace, or the capital, makes no impression on ignorant, proud, and prejudiced, minds; and, as for
            the concatenation of events, they are unable to trace, to foresee, or even to conceive, it. Politics, with its several springs and laws, must here be very much limited; the political government is as simple as the civil.*
            The whole is reduced to reconciling the political and civil administration to the domestic government, the officers of state to those of the seraglio.
            Such a state is happiest when it can look upon itself as the only one in the world, when it is environed with deserts, and separated from those people whom they call barbarians. Since it cannot depend on the militia, it is proper it should destroy a part of itself.
            As fear is the principle of despotic government, its end is tranquillity: but this tranquillity cannot be called a peace; no, it is only the silence of those towns which the enemy is ready to invade.
            Since the strength does not lie in the state, but in the army that founded it; in order to defend the state, the army must be preserved, how formidable soever to the prince. How, then, can we reconcile the security of the government to that of the prince’s person?
            Observe how industriously the Russian government endeavours to temper its arbitrary power, which it finds more burthensome than the people themselves. They have broke their numerous guards, mitigated criminal punishments, erected tribunals, entered into a knowledge of the laws, and instructed the people. But there are particular causes that will probably once more involve them in the very misery which they now endeavour to avoid.
            In those states religion has more influence than any where else: it is fear added to fear. In Mahometan countries it is partly from their religion that the people derive the surprizing veneration they have for their prince.
            It is religion that amends, in some measure, the Turkish constitution. The subjects, who have no attachment of honour to the glory and grandeur of the state, are connected with it by the force and principle of religion.
            Of all <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments there is none that labours more under its own weight than that wherein the prince declares himself proprietor of all the lands, and heir to all his subjects. Hence the neglect of agriculture arises; and, if the prince intermeddles likewise in trade, all manner of industry is ruined.
            Under this sort of government nothing is repaired or improved.† Houses are built only for the necessity of habitation: there is no digging of ditches, or planting of trees: every thing is drawn from, but nothing restored to, the earth: the ground lies untilled, and the whole country becomes a desert.
            Is it to be imagined, that the laws, which abolish the property of land and the succession of estates, will diminish the avarice and cupidity of the great? By no means: they will rather stimulate this cupidity and avarice. The great men will be
            prompted to use a thousand oppressive methods, imagining they have no other property than the gold and silver which they are able to seize upon by violence or to conceal.
            To prevent, therefore, the utter ruin of the state, the avidity of the prince ought to be moderated by some established custom. Thus, in Turkey, the sovereign is satisfied with the right of three per cent. on the value of inheritances.‡ But, as he gives the greatest part of the lands to his soldiery, and disposes of them as he pleases; as he seizes on all the inheritances of the officers of the empire at their decease; as he has the property of the possessions of those who die without issue, and the daughters have only the usufruct; it thence follows that the greatest part of the estates of the country are held in a precarious manner.
            By the laws of Bantam* the king seizes on the whole inheritance, even wife, children, and habitation. In order to elude the cruellest part of this law, they are obliged to marry their children at eight, nine, or ten years of <eligibility type="age">age</eligibility>, and sometimes younger, to the end that they may not be a wretched part of the father’s succession.
            In countries where there are no fundamental laws the succession to the empire cannot be fixed. The crown is then elective, and the right of electing is in the prince, who names a successor either of his own or of some other family. In vain would it be to establish here the succession of the eldest son: the prince might always choose another. The successor is declared by the prince himself, or by a civil war. Hence a despotic state is, upon another account, more liable, than a monarchical government, to dissolution.
            As every prince of the royal family is held equally capable of being chosen, hence it follows that the prince who ascends the throne immediately strangles his brothers, as in Turkey; or puts out their eyes, as in Persia; or bereaves them of their understanding, as in the Mogul’s country; or, if these precautions are not used, as in Morocco, the vacancy of the throne is always attended with the horrors of a civil war.
            By the constitutions of Russia† the Czar may choose whom he has a mind for his successor, whether of his own or of a strange family, Such a settlement produces a thousand revolutions, and renders the throne as tottering as the succession is arbitrary. The right of succession being one of those things which are of most importance to the people to know, the best is that which most sensibly strikes them, such as a certain order of birth. A settlement of this kind puts a stop to intrigues, and stifles ambition: the mind of a weak prince is no longer enslaved, nor is he made to speak his will as he is just expiring.
            When the succession is established by a fundamental law, only one prince is the successor, and his brothers have neither a real nor apparent right to dispute the crown with him. They can neither pretend to, nor take any advantage of, the will of a father. There is then no more occasion to confine or kill the king’s brother than any other subject.
            But, in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where the prince’s brothers are equally his slaves and his rivals, prudence requires that their persons be secured; especially in Mahometan countries, where religion considers victory or success as a divine decision in their favour; so that they have no such thing as a monarch de jure, but only de facto.
            There is a far greater incentive to ambition in countries where the princes of the blood are sensible, that, if they do not ascend the throne, they must be either imprisoned or put to death, than amongst us, where they are placed in such a station as may satisfy, if not their ambition, at least their moderate desires.
            The princes of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments have ever perverted the use of marriage. They generally take a great many wives, especially in that part of the world where absolute power is in some measure naturalized; namely, Asia. Hence they come to have such a multitude of children, that they can hardly have any great affection for them, nor the children for one another.
            The reigning family resembles the state: it is too weak itself, and its head too powerful: it seems very numerous and extensive, and yet is suddenly extinct. Artaxerxes‡ put all his children to death for conspiring against him. It is not at all probable that fifty children should conspire against their father, and much less that this conspiracy should be owing to his having refused to resign his concubine to his eldest son. It is more natural to believe that the whole was an intrigue of those oriental seraglios, where fraud, treachery, and deceit, reign in silence and darkness; and where an old prince, grown every day more infirm, is the first prisoner of the palace.
            After what has been said, one would imagine that human nature should perpetually rise up against despotism. But, notwithstanding the love of liberty, so natural to mankind, notwithstanding their innate detestation of force and violence, most nations are subject to this very government. This is easily accounted for. To form a moderate government, it is necessary to combine the several powers; to regulate, temper, and set them in motion; to give, as it were, ballast to one, in order to enable it to counterpoise the other. This is a master-piece of legislation, rarely produced by hazard, and seldom attained by prudence. On the contrary, a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government offers itself, as it were, at first sight; it is uniform throughout; and, as passions only are requisite to establish it, this is what every capacity may reach.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XV.</chapter>
            <subheading>The Same Subject Continued.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN warm climates, where despotic power generally prevails, the passions disclose themselves earlier, and are sooner extinguished? ; the understanding is sooner ripened; they are in less danger of squandering away their fortunes; there is less facility of distinguishing themselves in the world; less communication between young people, who are confined at home; they marry much earlier, and consequently may be sooner of age, than in our European climates. In Turkey, they are of <eligibility type="age">age</eligibility> at fifteen§ .
            They have no such thing as a cession of goods; in a government where there is no fixed property people depend rather on the person than on his estate.
            The cession of goods is naturally admitted in moderate governments* , but especially in republics, because of the greater confidence usually placed in the probity of the citizens, and the lenity and moderation arising from a form of government which every subject seems to have preferred to all others.
            Had the legislators of the Roman republic established the cession of goods† , they never would have been exposed to so many seditions and civil discords; neither would they have experienced the danger of the evils nor the inconveniency of the remedies.
            Poverty, and the precariousness of property, in a despotic state, render usury natural, each person raising the value of his money in proportion to the danger he sees in lending it. Misery, therefore, pours in from all parts into those unhappy countries; they are bereft of every thing, even of the resource of borrowing.
            Hence it is, that a merchant, under this government, is unable to carry on an extensive commerce: he lives from hand to mouth; and, were he to encumber himself with a large quantity of merchandises, he would lose more by the exorbitant interest he must give for money than he could possibly get by the goods. Hence they have no laws here relating to commerce; they are all reduced to what is called the bare police.
            A government cannot be unjust without having hands to exercise its injustice. Now, it is impossible but these hands will be grasping for themselves. The embezzling of the public money is, therefore, natural in despotic states.
            As this is a common crime, under such a government, confiscations are very useful. By these the people are eased; the money drawn by this method being a considerable tribute, which could hardly be raised on the exhausted subject: neither is there, in those countries, any one family which the prince would be glad to preserve.
            In moderate governments it is quite a different thing. Confiscations would render property uncertain, would strip innocent children, would destroy a whole family, instead of punishing a single criminal. In republics, they would be attended with the
            mischief of subverting equality, which is the very soul of this government, by depriving a citizen of his necessary subsistence.
            There is a Roman law‡ against confiscations, except in the case of crimen majestatis, or high treason of the most heinous nature. It would be a prudent thing to follow the spirit of this law, and to limit confiscations to particular crimes* . In countries where a local custom has rendered real estates alienable, Bodin very justly observes, that confiscations should extend only to such as are purchased or acquired? .
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVI.</chapter>
        <subheading>Of The Communication Of Power.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, the power is communicated entire to the person intrusted with it. The vizir himself is the despotic prince; and each particular officer is the vizir. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the power is less immediately applied, being tempered by the monarch as he gives it‡ . He makes such a distribution of his authority, as never to communicate a part of it without reserving a greater share to himself.
            Hence, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the governors of towns are not so dependent on the governor of the province as not to be still more so on the prince; and the private officers of military bodies are not so far subject to their general as not to owe still a greater subjection to their sovereign.
            In most <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, it has been wisely regulated, that those, who have an extensive command, should not belong to any military corps; so that, as they have no authority but through the prince’s pleasure, and as they may be employed or not, they are in some measure in the service, and in some measure out of it.
            This is incompatible with a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government. For, if those who are not actually employed were still invested with privileges and titles, the consequence must be, that there would be a kind of men in the state who might be said to be great of themselves; a thing directly opposite to the nature of this government.
            Were the governor of a town independent of the bashaw, expedients would be daily necessary to make them agree; which is highly absurd in a despotic state. Besides, if a particular governor might refuse to obey, how could the other answer for his province with his head?
            In this kind of government, authority must ever be wavering; nor is that of the lowest magistrate more steady than that of the despotic prince. Under moderate governments, the law is prudent in all its parts, and perfectly well known, so that even the pettiest magistrates are capable of following it. But, in a despotic state, where the prince’s will is the law, though the prince were wise, yet how could the magistrate follow a will he does not know? he must certainly follow his own.
            Again, as the law is only the prince’s will, and as the prince can only will what he knows, the consequence is, that there are an infinite number of people who must will for him, and make their wills keep pace with his.
            In fine, as the law is the momentary will of the prince, it is necessary that those who will for him should follow his subitaneous manner of willing.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVII.</chapter>
        <subheading>Of Presents.</subheading>
        <p>
            IT is a received custom, in despotic countries, never to address any superior whomsoever, not excepting their kings, without making them a present. The Mogul† never receives the petitions of his subjects if they come with empty hands. These princes spoil even their own favours.
            But thus it must ever be in a government where no man is a citizen; where they have all a notion that a superior is under no obligation to an inferior; where men imagine themselves bound by no other tie than the chastisements inflicted by one party over another; where, in fine, there is very little to do, and where the people have seldom an occasion of presenting themselves before the great, of offering their petitions, and much less their complaints.
            In a republic, presents are odious, because virtue stands in no need of them. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, honour is a much stronger incentive than presents. But, in a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, where there is neither honour nor virtue, people cannot be determined to act but through hope of the conveniences of life.
            It is in conformity to republican ideas, that Plato‡ ordered those who received presents for doing their duty to be punished with death. “They must not take presents (says he) neither for good nor for evil actions.”
            A very bad law that was, among the Romans? , which gave the magistrates leave to accept of small presents§ , provided they did not exceed one hundred crowns the whole year. They, who receive nothing, expect nothing; they, who receive a little, soon covet more; till at length their desires swell to an exorbitant height. Besides, it is much easier to convict a man, who knows himself obliged to accept of no present at all, and yet will accept of something, than a person who takes more when he ought to take less, and who always finds pretexts, excuses, and plausible reasons, in justification of his conduct.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Rewards Conferred By The Sovereign.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where, as we have already observed, the principal motive of action is the hope of the conveniences of life, the prince who confers rewards has nothing to bestow but money. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, where honour alone predominates, the prince’s rewards would consist only of marks of distinction, if the distinctions established by honour were not attended with luxury, which necessarily brings on its wants: the prince, therefore, is obliged to confer such honours as lead to wealth. But, in a republic, where virtue reigns, (a motive self-sufficient, and which excludes all others,) the recompences of the state consist only of public attestations of this virtue.
            It is a general rule, that great rewards, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> and republics, are a sign of their decline, because they are a proof of their principles being corrupted, and that the idea of honour has no longer the same force in <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, nor the title of citizen the same weight in a republic.
            The very worst Roman emperors were those who were most profuse in their largesses; for example, Caligula, Claudius, Nero, Otho, Vitellius, Commodus, Heliogabalus, and Caracalla. The best, as Augustus, Vespasian, Antoninus Pius, Marcus Aurelius, and Pertinax, were œconomists. Under good emperors the state resumed its principles; all other treasures were supplied by that of honour.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIX.</chapter>
            <subheading>New Consequences Of The Principles Of The Three Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            I cannot conclude this book without making some applications of my three principles.
            Quest. 1. It is a question, whether the laws ought to oblige a subject to accept of a public employment. My opinion is, that they ought in a republic, but not in a monarchical government. In the former, public employments are attestations of virtue, depositums with which a citizen is entrusted by his country, for whose sake alone he ought to live, to act, and to think; consequently, he cannot refuse them¶ . In the latter, public offices are testimonies of honour: now, such is the capriciousness of honour, that it chooses to accept of none of these testimonies but when and in what manner it pleases.
            The late king of Sardinia inflicted punishments* on his subjects who refused the dignities and public offices of the state. In this he unknowingly followed republican ideas: but his manner of governing, in other respects, sufficiently proves that this was not his intention.
            Quest. 2. Secondly, it is questioned, whether a subject should be obliged to accept of a post in the army inferior to that which he held before. Among the Romans, it was usual to see a captain serve the next year under his lieutenant† . This is because virtue in republics requires a continual sacrifice of our persons and of our repugnances for the good of the state. But, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, honour, true or false, will never bear with what it calls degrading itself.
            In <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where honour, posts, and ranks, are equally abused, they indiscriminately make of a prince a scullion, and of a scullion a prince.
            Quest. 3. Thirdly, it may be enquired, whether civil and military employments should be conferred on the same person. In republics, I think, they should be joined, but in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> separated. In the former, it would be extremely dangerous to make the profession of arms a particular state, distinct from that of civil functions; and, in the latter, no less dangerous would it be to confer these two employments on the same person.
            In republics, a person takes up arms only with a view to defend his country and its laws; it is because he is a citizen he makes himself, for a while, a soldier. Were these two distinct states, the person who, under arms, thinks himself a citizen, would soon be made sensible he is only a soldier.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, they, whose condition engages them in the profession of arms, have nothing but glory, or, at least, honour or fortune, in view. To men, therefore, like
            these, the prince should never give any civil employments; on the contrary, they ought to be checked by the civil magistrate, that the same persons may not have, at the same time, the confidence of the people and the power to abuse it‡ .
            We have only to cast an eye on a nation that may be justly called a republic disguised under the form of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, and we shall see how jealous they are of making a separate order of the profession of arms, and how the military state is constantly allied with that of the citizen, and even sometimes of the magistrate, to the end that these qualities may be a pledge for their country which should never be forgotten.
            The division of civil and military employments, made by the Romans after the extinction of the republic, was not an arbitrary thing: it was a consequence of the change which happened in the constitution of Rome; it was natural to a monarchical government; and, what was only commenced under Augustus? , succeeding emperors§ were obliged to finish, in order to temper the military government.
            Procopius, therefore, the competitor of Valens, the emperor, was very much to blame, when, conferring the proconsular dignity¶ upon Hormisdas, a prince of the blood- royal of Persia, he restored to this magistracy the military command of which it had been formerly possessed, unless, indeed, he had very particular reasons for so doing. A person, that aspires to the sovereignty, concerns himself less about what is serviceable to the state than what is likely to promote his own interest.
            Quest. 4. Fourthly, it is a question, whether public employments should be sold. They ought not, I think, in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where the subjects must be instantaneously placed or displaced by the prince.
            But, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, this custom is not at all improper, by reason it is an inducement to engage in that, as a family employment, which would not be undertaken through a motive of virtue: it fixes, likewise, every one to his duty, and renders the several orders of the kingdom more permanent. Suidas* very justly observes, that Anastasius had changed the empire into a kind of aristocracy, by selling all public employments.
            Plato† cannot bear with this prostitution: “This is exactly (says he) as if a person were to be made a mariner or pilot of a ship for his money. Is it possible that this rule should be bad in every other employment of life and hold good only in the administration of a republic?” But Plato speaks of a republic founded on virtue, and we of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>. Now, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, (where, though there were no such thing as a regular sale of public offices, still the indigence and avidity of the courtier would equally prompt him to expose them to sale,) chance will furnish better subjects than the prince’s choice. In short, the method of attaining to honours through riches inspires and cherishes industry‡ , a thing extremely wanting in this kind of government.
            Quest. 5. The fifth question is, in what kind of government censors are necessary. My answer is, that they are necessary in a republic, where the principle of government is virtue. We must not imagine that criminal actions only are destructive of virtue; it is destroyed also by omissions, by neglects, by a certain coolness in the love of our
            country, by bad examples, and by the seeds of corruption. Whatever does not openly violate, but elude, the laws; does not subvert, but weaken, them; ought to fall under the enquiry and correction of the censors.
            We are surprised at the punishment of the Areopagite for killing a sparrow, which, to escape the pursuit of a hawk, had taken shelter in his bosom. Surprised we are, also, that an Areopagite should put his son to death for pulling out the eyes of a little bird. But let us reflect, that the question here does not relate to a criminal sentence, but to a judgement concerning manners in a republic founded on manners.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> there should be no censors: the former are founded on honour, and the nature of honour is to have the whole world for its censor. Every man who fails in this article is subject to the reproaches even of those who are void of honour.
            Here the censors would be spoilt by the very people whom they ought to correct: they could not prevail against the corruption of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>; the corruption rather would be too strong against them.
            Hence it is obvious, that there ought to be no censors in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments. The example of China seems to derogate from this rule: but we shall see, in the course of this work, the particular reasons of that institution.
        </p>
    </book>
    
    <book>BOOK VI.
        <heading>CONSEQUENCES OF THE PRINCIPLES OF DIFFERENT GOVERNMENTS WITH RESPECT TO THE SIMPLICITY OF CIVIL AND CRIMINAL LAWS, THE FORM OF JUDGEMENTS, AND THE INFLICTING OF PUNISHMENTS.</heading>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Simplicity Of Civil Laws In Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            MONARCHIES do not permit of so great a simplicity of laws as <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments: for, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, there must be courts of judicature: these must give their decisions: the decisions must be preserved and learnt, that we may judge in the same manner to-day as yesterday, and that the lives and property of the citizens may be as certain and fixt as the very constitution of the state.
            In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the administration of justice, which decides not only in whatever belongs to life and property, but likewise to honour, demands very scrupulous enquiries. The delicacy of the judge increases in proportion to the increase of his trust, and of the importance of the interests on which he determines.
            We must not therefore be surprised to find so many rules, restrictions, and extensions, in the laws of those countries; rules that multiply the particular cases, and seem to make of reason itself an art.
            The difference of rank, birth, and condition, established in monarchical governments, is frequently attended with distinctions in the nature of property; and the laws relative to the constitution of this government may augment the number of these distinctions. Hence, among us, goods are divided into real estates, purchases, dowries, paraphernalia, paternal and maternal inheritances; moveables of different kinds; estates held in fee-simple or in tail; acquired by descent or conveyance; allodial, or held by soccage; ground-rents, or annuities. Each sort of goods is subject to particular rules, which must be complied with in the disposal of them. These things must needs diminish the simplicity of the laws.
            In our governments the fiefs are become hereditary. It was necessary that the nobility should have a fixt property; that is, the fief should have a certain consistency; to the end that the proprietor might be always in a capacity of serving the prince. This must have been productive of great varieties: for instance, there are countries where fiefs could not be divided among the brothers; in others, the younger brothers may be allowed a more generous subsistence.
            The monarch, who knows each of his provinces, may establish different laws, or tolerate different customs. But, as the despotic prince knows nothing, and can attend to nothing, he must take general measures, and govern by a rigid and inflexible will, which, throughout his whole dominions, produces the same effect: in short, every thing bends under his feet.
            In proportion as the decisions of the courts of judicature are multiplied in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the law is loaded with decrees that sometimes contradict one another; either because succeeding judges are of a different way of thinking, or because the same causes are sometimes well, and at other times ill, defended; or, in fine, by reason of an infinite number of abuses, to which all human regulations are liable. This is a necessary evil, which the legislator redresses from time to time, as contrary even to the spirit of moderate governments: for, when people are obliged to have recourse to courts of judicature, this should come from the nature of the constitution, and not from the contradiction or uncertainty of the law.
            In governments where there are necessary distinctions of persons there must likewise be privileges. This also diminishes the simplicity, and creates a thousand exceptions.
            One of the privileges least burthensome to society, and especially to him who confers it, is that of pleading in one court preferably to another. Here new difficulties arise, when it becomes a question before which court we shall plead.
            Far different is the case of the people under <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments. In those countries I can see nothing that the legislator is able to decree, or the magistrate to judge. As the lands belong to the prince, it follows that there are scarce any civil laws in regard to landed property. From the right the sovereign has to successions it follows likewise that there are none relating to inheritances. The monopolies, established by the prince for himself in some countries, render all sorts of commercial laws quite useless. The marriages, which they usually contract with female slaves, are the cause that there are scarce any civil laws relating to dowries, or to the particular advantage of married women. From the prodigious multitude of slaves it follows likewise that there are very few who have any such thing as a will of their own, and of course are answerable for their conduct before a judge. Most moral actions, that are only in consequence of a father’s, a husband’s, or a master’s, will, are regulated by them, and not by the magistrates.
            I forgot to observe, that, as what we call honour is a thing hardly known in those countries, the several difficulties relating to this article, though of such importance with us, are with them quite out of the question. Despotic power is self-sufficient: round it there is an absolute vacuum. Hence it is, that, when travellers favour us with the description of countries where arbitrary sway prevails, they seldom make mention of civil laws.*
            All occasions, therefore, of wrangling and lawsuits are here removed. And to this, in part, it is owing that litigious people, in those countries, are so roughly handled: as the injustice of their demand is neither screened, palliated, nor protected, by an infinite number of laws, of course it is immediately discovered.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Simplicity Of Criminal Laws In Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            WE hear it generally said, that justice ought to be administered with us as in Turkey. Is it possible, then, that the most ignorant of all nations should be the most clear- sighted in a point which it most behoves mankind to know?
            If we examine the set forms of justice, with respect to the trouble the subject undergoes, in recovering his property, or in obtaining satisfaction for an injury or affront, we shall find them doubtless too numerous: but, if we consider them in the relation they bear to the liberty and security of every individual, we shall often find them too few, and be convinced that the trouble, expence, delays, and even the very dangers, of our judiciary proceedings, are the price that each subject pays for his liberty.
            In Turkey, where little regard is shewn to the honour, life, or estate, of the subject, all causes are speedily decided. The method of determining them is a matter of indifference, provided they be determined. The bashaw, after a quick hearing, orders which party he pleases to be bastinadoed, and then sends them about their business.
            Here it would be dangerous to be of a litigious disposition: this supposes a strong desire of obtaining justice, a settled aversion, an active mind, and a steadiness in pursuing one’s point. All this should be avoided in a government where fear ought to be the only prevailing sentiment, and in which popular disturbances are frequently attended with sudden and unforeseen revolutions. Here every man ought to know that the magistrate must not hear his name mentioned, and that his security depends entirely on his being reduced to a kind of annihilation.
            But, in moderate governments, where the life of the meanest subject is deemed precious, no man is stript of his honour or property but after a long enquiry; and no man is bereft of life till his very country has attacked him; an attack that is never made without leaving him all possible means of making his defence.
            Hence it is, that, when a person renders himself absolute* , he immediately thinks of reducing the number of laws. In a government thus constituted, they are more affected with particular inconveniences than with the liberty of the subject, which is very little minded.
            In republics, it is plain, that as many formalities, at least, are necessary as in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>. In both governments, they increase in proportion to the value which is set on the honour, fortune, liberty, and life, of the subject.
            In republican governments, men are all equal; equal they are, also, in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments: in the former, because they are every thing; in the latter, because they are nothing.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Governments, And In What Cases, The Judges Ought To Determine According To The Express Letter Of The Law.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE nearer the government approaches towards a republic, the more the manner of judging becomes settled and fixt: hence it was a fault, in the republic of Sparta, for the Ephori to pass such arbitrary judgements, without having any laws to direct them. The first consuls, at Rome, pronounced sentence in the same manner as the Ephori; but the inconveniency of this proceeding was soon felt, and they were obliged to have recourse to express and determinate laws.
            In <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments there are no laws; the judge himself is his own rule. There are laws in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>; and, where these are explicit, the judge conforms to them; where they are otherwise, he endeavours to investigate their spirit. In republics, the very nature of the constitution requires the judges to follow the letter of the law; otherwise, the law might be explained to the prejudice of every citizen, in cases where their honour, property, or life, are concerned.
            At Rome, the judges had no more to do than to declare that the person accused was guilty of a particular crime, and then the punishment was found in the laws, as may be seen in divers laws still extant. In England, the jury give their verdict, whether the fact, brought under their cognizance, be proved or not; if it be proved, the judge pronounces the punishment inflicted by the law, and for this he needs only to open his eyes.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Manner Of Passing Judgement.</subheading>
        <p>
            HENCE arises the different manner of passing judgement. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> the judges choose the method of arbitration: they deliberate together; they communicate their sentiments for the sake of unanimity; they moderate their opinions, in order to render them conformable to those of others; and the lesser number is obliged to give way to the majority. But this is not agreeable to the nature of a republic. At Rome, and in the cities of Greece, the judges never entered into a consultation; each gave his opinion one of these three ways; I absolve; I condemn; it does not appear clear to me* : this was because the people judged, or were supposed to judge. But the people are far from being civilians; all these restrictions and methods of arbitration are above their reach; they must have only one object, and one single fact, set before them; and then they have only to see whether they ought to condemn, to acquit, or to suspend their judgement.
            The Romans introduced fet forms of actions† , after the example of the Greeks, and established a rule, that each cause should be directed by its proper action. This was necessary in their manner of judging; it was necessary to fix the state of the question, that the people might have it always before their eyes: otherwise, in a long process, this state of the question would continually change, and be no longer distinguished.
            Hence it followed, that the Roman judges granted only the simple demand, without making any addition, deduction, or limitation. But the prætors devised other forms of actions, which were called ex bona fide, where the method of pronouncing sentence was left to the disposition of the judge. This was more agreeable to the spirit of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>. Hence it is a saying among the French lawyers, that, in France‡ , all actions areex bona fide.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
            <subheading>In What Governments The Sovereign May Be Judge.</subheading>
        <p>
            MACHIAVEL§ attributes the loss of the liberty of Florence to the people’s not judging in a body in cases of high-treason against themselves, as was customary at Rome. For this purpose they had eight judges: but the few, says Machiavel, are corrupted by a few. I should willingly adopt the maxim of this great man: but as, in those cases, the political interest prevails, in some measure, over the civil, (for it is always an inconveniency that the people should be judges in their own cause,) in order to remedy this evil, the laws must provide as much as possible for the security of individuals.
            With this view, the Roman legislators did two things; they gave the persons accused permission to banish themselves? before sentence was pronounced¶ ; and they ordained, that the goods of those who were condemned should be sacred, to prevent their being confiscated to the people. We shall see, in the XIth book, the other limitations that were set to the judicatory power residing in the people.
            <person type="Solon">Solon</person> knew how to prevent the abuse which the people might make of their power in criminal judgements. He ordained, that the court of Areopagus should re-examine the affair; that, if they believed the party accused was unjustly acquitted* , they should impeach him again before the people; that, if they believed him unjustly condemned† , they should prevent the execution of the sentence, and make them re-judge the proceeding. An admirable law, that subjected the people to the censure of the magistracy which they most revered, and even to their own!
            In affairs of this kind, it is always proper to throw in some delays, especially when the party accused is under confinement; to the end that the people may grow calm, and give their judgement coolly.
            In <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, the prince himself may be judge: but in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments> this cannot be; the constitution by such means would be subverted, and the dependent intermediate powers annihilated; all set forms of judgement would cease; fear would take possession of the people’s minds, and paleness spread itself over every countenance: the more confidence, honour, affection, and security, in the subject, the more extended is the power of the monarch.
            We shall give here a few more reflections on this point. In <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, the prince is the party that prosecutes the person accused, and causes him to be punished or acquitted; now, were he himself to sit upon the trial, he would be both judge and party.
            In this government the prince has frequently the benefit of confiscation; so that here again, by determining criminal causes, he would be both judge and party.
            Farther, by this method, he would deprive himself of the most glorious attribute of sovereignty, namely, that of granting pardon* ; for it would be quite ridiculous of him to make and unmake his decisions: surely, he would not choose to contradict himself.
            Besides, this would be confounding all ideas; it would be impossible to tell whether a man was acquitted or received his pardon.
            Lewis XIII. being desirous to sit in judgement upon the trial of the duke ae la Valette† , sent for some members of the parliament and of the privy-council to debate the matter. Upon their being ordered by the king to give their opinion concerning the warrant for his arrest, the president de Believre said, “That he found it very strange a prince should pass sentence upon a subject: that kings had reserved to themselves the power of pardoning, and left that of condemning to their officers: that his majesty wanted to see before him at the bar a person, who, by his decision, was to be hurried away into the other world: that the prince’s countenance should inspire with hopes, and not confound with fears: that his presence alone removed ecclesiastic censures: and that subjects ought not to go away dissatisfied from the sovereign.” When sentence was passed, the same magistrate declared, “This is an unprecedented judgement; to see, contrary to the example of past ages, a king of France, in the quality of a judge, condemning a gentleman to death‡ .”
            Again, sentences passed by the prince would be an inexhaustible source of injustice and abuse; the courtiers, by their importunity, would always be able to extort his decisions. Some Roman emperors were so mad as to sit as judges themselves; the consequence was, that no reigns ever so surprized the world with oppression and injustice.
            “Claudius, (says Tacitus? ,) having appropriated to himself the determination of law suits and the function of magistrates, gave occasion to all manner of rapine.” But Nero, upon coming to the empire after Claudius, endeavoured to conciliate the minds of the people, by declaring, “That he would take care not to be judge himself in private causes, that the parties might not be exposed, within the walls of a palace, to the iniquitous influence of a few freedmen§ .”
            “Under the reign of Arcadius, (says Zozimus¶ ,) a swarm of calumniators spread themselves on every side, and infected the court. Upon a person’s decease, it was immediately supposed he had left no children* ; and, in consequence of this, his property was given away by a recript. For, as the prince was surprizingly stupid, and the empress excessively enterprizing, she was a slave to the insatiable avarice of her domestics and confidents; insomuch, that, to an honest man, nothing could be more desirable than death.”
            “Formerly, (says Procopius† ,) there used to be very few people at court; but, in Justinian’s reign, as the judges had no longer the liberty of administering justice, their tribunals were deserted, while the prince’s palace resounded with the litigious clamours of the several parties.” Every body knows what a prostitution there was of public judgements, and even of the very laws themselves, at the emperor’s court.
            The laws are the eye of the prince; by them he sees what would otherwise escape his observation. Should he attempt the function of a judge, he would not then labour for himself, but for impostors, whose aim is to deceive him.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VI.</chapter>
            <subheading>That, In Monarchies, Ministers Ought Not To Sit As Judges.</subheading>
        <p>
            IT is, likewise, a very great inconveniency, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, for the ministers of the prince to sit as judges. We have still instances of states where there is a great number of judges to decide exchequer causes, and where the ministers, nevertheless, (a thing most incredible,) would fain determine them. Many are the reflections that here arise; but this single one will suffice for my purpose.
            There is, in the very nature of things, a kind of contrast between a prince’s council and his courts of judicature. The king’s council ought to be composed of a few persons, and the courts of judicature of a great many. The reason is, in the former, things should be undertaken and conducted with a kind of warmth and passion, which can hardly be expected but from four or five men who make it their sole business. On the contrary, in courts of judicature, a certain coolness is requisite, and an indifference, in some measure, to all manner of affairs.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of A Single Magistrate.</subheading>
        <p>
            A magistracy of this kind cannot take place but in a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government. We have an instance, in the Roman history, how far a single magistrate may abuse his power. Might it not be very well expected that Appius, on his tribunal, should contemn all laws, after having violated that of his own‡ enacting? Livy has given us the iniquitous distinction of the decemvir. He had suborned a man to reclaim Virginia, in his presence, as his slave: Virginia’s relations insisted, that, by virtue of his own law, she should be consigned to them till the definitive judgement was passed. Upon which, he declared, that his law had been enacted only in favour of the father; and that, as Virginius was absent, no application could be made of it to the present case? .
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. VIII.</chapter>
        <subheading>Of Accusation In Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            AT Rome§ it was lawful for one citizen to accuse another: this was agreeable to the spirit of a republic, where each citizen ought to have an unlimited zeal for the public good, and is supposed to hold all the rights of his country in his own hands. Under the emperors the republican maxims were still pursued; and instantly appeared a pernicious tribe, a swarm of informers. Crafty wicked men, who could stoop to any indignity to serve the purposes of their ambition, were sure to busy themselves in the search of criminals whose condemnation might be agreeable to the prince: this was the road to honour and preferment¶ : but luckily we are strangers to it in our country.
            We have at present an admirable law, namely, that by which the prince, who is established for the execution of the laws, appoints an officer in each court of judicature to prosecute all sorts of crimes in his name: hence the profession of informers is a thing unknown to us; for, if this public avenger were suspected to abuse his office, he would soon be obliged to mention his author.
            By Plato’s laws* , those who neglect to inform or assist the magistrates are liable to punishment. This would not be so proper in our days. The public prosecutor warches for the safety of the citizens; he proceeds in his office while they enjoy their quiet and ease.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. IX.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Severity Of Punishments In Different Governments.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE severity of punishments is fitter for <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, whose principle is terror, than for a <governments type="groups_of_government">monarchy or a republic</governments>, whose spring is honour and virtue.
            In moderate governments, the love of one’s country, shame, and the fear of blame, are restraining motives, capable of preventing a multitude of crimes. Here the greatest punishment of a bad action is conviction. The civil laws have, therefore, a softer way of correcting, and do not require so much force and severity.
            In those states, a good legislator is less bent upon punishing, than preventing, crimes; he is more attentive to inspire good morals than to inflict penalties.
            It is a constant remark of the Chinese authors† , that, the more the penal laws were increased in their empire, the nearer they drew towards a revolution. This is because punishments were augmented in proportion as the public morals were corrupted.
            It would be an easy matter to prove, that, in all, or almost all, the governments of Europe, penalties have increased or diminished in proportion as those governments favoured or discouraged liberty.
            In <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, people are so unhappy as to have a greater dread of death than regret for the loss of life; consequently, their punishments ought to be more severe. In moderate states, they are more afraid of losing their lives than apprehensive of the pain of dying; those punishments, therefore, which deprive them simply of life, are sufficient.
            Men, in excess of happiness or misery, are equally inclinable to severity; witness conquerors and monks. It is mediocrity alone, and a mixture of prosperous and adverse fortune, that inspire us with lenity and pity.
            What we see practised by individuals is equally observable in regard to nations. In countries inhabited by savages, who lead a very hard life, and in <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where there is only one person on whom fortune lavishes her favours, while the miserable subjects lie exposed to her insults, people are equally cruel. Lenity reigns in moderate governments.
            When, in reading history, we observe the cruelty of the sultans in the administration of justice, we shudder at the very thought of the miseries of human nature.
            In moderate governments, a good legislator may make use of every thing by way of punishment. Is it not very extraordinary, that one of the chief penalties, at Sparta, was to deprive a person of the power of lending out his wife, or of receiving the wife of
            another man, and to oblige him to have no company at home but virgins? In short, whatever the law calls a punishment, is such effectively.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. X.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Ancient French Laws.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN the ancient French laws we find the true spirit of monarchy. In cases relating to pecuniary mulcts, the common people are less severely punished than the nobility‡ : but in criminal? cases it is quite the reverse; the nobleman loses his honour and his voice in court, while the peasant, who has no honour to lose, undergoes a corporal punishment.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XI.</chapter>
            <subheading>That, When People Are Virtuous, Few Punishments Are Necessary.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE people of Rome had some share of probity. Such was the force of this probity, that the legislator had frequently no farther occasion than to point out the right road, and they were sure to follow it. One would imagine, that, instead of precepts, it was sufficient to give them counsels.
            The punishments of the regal laws, and those of the twelve tables, were almost all abolished in the time of the republic, in consequence either of the Valerian§ or of the Porcian law.¶ It was never observed that this step did any manner of prejudice to the civil administration.
            This Valerian law, which restrained the magistrates from using violent methods against a citizen that had appealed to the people, inflicted no other punishment on the person who infringed it than that of being reputed a dishonest man.*
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Power Of Punishments.</subheading>
        <p>
            EXPERIENCE shews, that, in countries remarkable for the lenity of their laws, the spirit of the inhabitants is as much affected, by slight penalties, as in other countries by severer punishments.
            If an inconveniency or abuse arises in the state, a violent government endeavours suddenly to redress it; and, instead of putting the old laws in execution, it establishes some cruel punishment, which instantly puts a stop to the evil. But the spring of government hereby loses its elasticity; the imagination grows accustomed to the severe as well as the milder punishment; and, as the fear of the latter diminishes, they are soon obliged, in every case, to have recourse to the former. Robberies on the high- way were grown common in some countries. In order to remedy this evil, they invented the punishment of breaking upon the wheel; the terror of which put a stop, for a while, to this mischievous practice: but, soon after, robberies on the highways became as common as ever.
            Desertion, in our days, was grown to a very great height: in consequence of which it was judged proper to punish those delinquents with death; and yet their number did not diminish. The reason is very natural: a soldier, accustomed to venture his life, despises, or affects to despise, the danger of losing it: he is habituated to the fear of shame: it would have been, therefore, much better to have continued a punishment† which branded him with infamy for life: the penalty was pretended to be increased, while it really diminished.
            Mankind must not be governed with too much severity: we ought to make a prudent use of the means which nature has given us to conduct them. If we enquire into the cause of all human corruptions, we shall find that they proceed from the impunity of criminals, and not from the moderation of punishments.
            Let us follow nature, who has given shame to man for his scourge; and let the heaviest part of the punishment be the infamy attending it.
            But, if there be some countries where shame is not a consequence of punishment, this must be owing to tyranny, which has inflicted the same penalties on villains and honest men.
            And, if there are others where men are deterred only by cruel punishments, we may be sure that this must, in a great measure, arise from the violence of the government, which has used such penalties for slight transgressions.
            It often happens, that a legislator, desirous of remedying an abuse, thinks of nothing else: his eyes are open only to this object, and shut to its inconveniences. When the abuse is redressed, you see only the severity of the legislator: yet there remains an evil
            in the state, that has sprung from this severity; the minds of the people are corrupted and become habituated to despotism.
            Lysander‡ having obtained a victory over the Athenians, the prisoners were ordered to be tried, in consequence of an accusation, brought against that nation, of having thrown all the captives of two galleys down a precipice, and of having resolved, in full assembly, to cut off the hands of those whom they should chance to make prisoners. The Athenians were therefore all massacred, except Adymantes, who had opposed this decree. Lysander reproached Philocles, before he was put to death, with having depraved the people’s minds, and given lessons of cruelty to all Greece.
            “The Argives (says Plutarch? ) having put fifteen hundred of their citizens to death, the Athenians ordered sacrifices of expiation, that it might please the gods to turn the hearts of the Athenians from so cruel a thought.”
            There are two sorts of corruption; one when the people do not observe the laws; the other when they are corrupted by the laws: an incurable evil, because it is in the very remedy itself.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Insufficiency Of The Laws Of Japan.</subheading>
        <p>
            <justice type="cruel_and_unusual_punishment">EXCESSIVE punishments may even corrupt a despotic government: of this we have an instance in Japan.
            Here almost all crimes are punished with death,§ because disobedience to so great an emperor as that of Japan is reckoned an enormous crime. The question is not so much to correct the delinquent, as to vindicate the authority of the prince. These notions are derived from servitude, and are owing especially to this, that, as the emperor is universal proprietor, almost all crimes are directly against his interests.
            They punish with death lies spoken before the magistrate¶ ; a proceeding contrary to natural defence.
            Even things which have not the appearance of a crime are severely punished: for instance, a man that ventures his money at play is put to death.
            True it is, that the character of this people, so amazingly obstinate, capricious, and resolute, as to defy all dangers and calamities, seems to absolve their legislators from the imputation of cruelty, notwithstanding the severity of their laws. But are men, who have a natural contempt of death, and who rip open their bellies for the least fancy; are such men, I say, mended or deterred, or rather are they not hardened, by the continual prospect of punishments?
            The relations of travellers inform us, with respect to the education of the Japanese, that children must be treated there with mildness, because they become hardened to punishment; that their slaves must not be too roughly used, because they immediately stand upon their defence. Would not one imagine that they might easily have judged of the spirit, which ought to reign in their political and civil government, from that which should prevail in their domestic concerns?
            A wise legislator would have endeavoured to reclaim people by a just temperature of punishments and rewards; by maxims of philosophy, morality, and religion, adapted to those characters; by a proper application of the rules of honour; and by the enjoyment of ease and tranquillity of life: and, should he have entertained any apprehension that their minds, being inured to the cruelty of punishments, would no longer be restrained by those of a milder nature, he would have conducted himself* in another manner, and gained his point by degrees: in particular cases, that admitted of any indulgence, he would have mitigated the punishment, till he should have been able to extend this mitigation to all cases.
            But these are springs to which despotic power is a stranger: it may abuse itself, and that is all it can do. In Japan it has made its utmost effort, and has surpassed even itself in cruelty.
            As the minds of the people grew wild and intractable, they were obliged to have recourse to the most horrid severity.
            This is the origin, this the spirit, of the laws of Japan. They had more fury, however, than force. They succeeded in the extirpation of Christianity: but such unaccountable efforts are a proof of their insufficiency. They wanted to establish a good polity, and they have shewn greater marks of their weakness.
            We have only to read the relation of the interview between the emperor and the deyro at Meaco.† The number of those who were suffocated or murdered in that city by ruffians is incredible: young maids and boys were carried off by force, and found afterwards exposed in public places, at unseasonable hours, quite naked, and sewed in linen bags, to prevent their knowing which way they had passed; robberies were committed in all parts; the bellies of horses were ripped open, to bring their riders to the ground; and coaches were overturned, in order to strip the ladies. The Dutch, who were told they could not pass the night on the scaffolds without exposing themselves to the danger of being assassinated, came down, and c.
            I shall here give one instance more from the same nation. The emperor, having abandoned himself to infamous pleasures, lived unmarried, and was consequently in danger of dying without issue. The deyro sent him two beautiful damsels; one he married out of respect, but would not meddle with her. His nurse caused the finest women of the empire to be sent for; but all to no purpose. At length, an armourer’s daughter having pleased his fancy,‡ he determined to espouse her, and had a son. The ladies belonging to court, enraged to see a person of such mean extraction preferred to themselves, stifled the child. The crime was concealed from the emperor; for he would have deluged the land with blood. The excessive severity of the laws hinders, therefore, their execution: when the punishment surpasses all measure, they are frequently obliged to prefer impunity to it.</justice>
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Spirit Of The Roman Senate.</subheading>
        <p>
            UNDER the consulate of Acilius Glabrio and Piso the Acilian law? was made, to prevent the intriguing for places. Dio says,§ that the senate engaged the consuls to propose it, by reason that C. Cornelius, the tribune, had resolved to cause more severe punishments to be established against this crime; to which the people seemed greatly inclined. The senate rightly judged, that immoderate punishments would strike indeed a terror into people’s minds, but must have also this effect, that there would be nobody afterwards to accuse or condemn; whereas, by proposing moderate penalties, there would be always judges and accusers.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XV.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Roman Laws In Respect To Punishments.</subheading>
        <p>
            I am strongly confirmed in my sentiments, upon finding the Romans on my side; and I think that punishments are connected with the nature of government, when I behold this great people changing, in this respect, their civil laws, in proportion as they altered their form of government.
            The regal laws made for fugitives, slaves, and vagabonds, were very severe. The spirit of a republic would have required that the decemvirs should not have inserted those laws in their twelve tables; but men who aimed at tyranny were far from conforming to a republican spirit.
            Livy says,¶ in relation to the punishment of Metius Suffetius, dictator of Alba, (who was condemned, by Tullius Hostilius, to be fastened to two chariots drawn by horses, and to be torn asunder,) that this was the first and last punishment in which the remembrance of humanity seemed to have been lost. He is mistaken: the twelve tables are full of very cruel laws.*
            The design of the decemvirs appears more conspicuous in the capital punishment pronounced against libellers and poets. This is not agreeable to the genius of a republic, where the people like to see the great men humbled: but persons who aimed at the subversion of liberty were afraid of writings that might revive its spirit†
            After the expulsion of the decemvirs, almost all the penal laws were abolished. It is true, they were not expressly repealed; but, as the Porcian law had ordained that no citizen of Rome should be put to death, they were of no farther use.
            This is exactly the time to which we may refer what Livy says¶ of the Romans, that no people were ever fonder of moderation in punishments.
            But, if, to the lenity of the penal laws, we add the right which the party accused had of withdrawing before judgement was pronounced, we shall find that the Romans followed the spirit which I have observed to be natural to a republic.
            <person type="Sylla">Sylla</person>, who confounded tyranny, anarchy, and liberty, made the Cornelian laws. He seemed to have contrived regulations merely with a view to create new crimes. Thus, distinguishing an infinite number of actions by the name of murder, he found murderers in all parts; and, by a practice but too much followed, he laid snares, sowed thorns, and opened precipices, wheresoever the citizens set their feet.
            Almost all<person type="Sylla">Sylla’s</person> laws contained only the interdiction of fire and water. To this Cæsar added the confiscation of goods* , because the rich, by preserving their estates in exile, became bolder in the perpetration of crimes.
            The emperors, having established a military government, soon found that it was as terrible to the prince as to the subject; they endeavoured, therefore, to temper it; and with this view had recourse to dignities, and to the respect with which those dignities were attended.
            The government thus drew nearer a little to <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, and punishments were divided into three classes† ; those which related to the principal persons in the state‡ , which were very mild; those which were inflicted on persons of an inferior rank? , and which were more severe; and, in fine, such as concerned only persons of the lowest condition§ , which were the most rigorous.
            Maximinus, that fierce, that stupid, prince, increased the rigour of the military government which he ought to have softened. The senate was informed, says Capitolinus¶ , that some had been crucified, others exposed to wild beasts, or sewed up in the skins of beasts lately killed, without any manner of regard to their dignity. It seemed as if he wanted to exercise the military discipline, on the model of which he pretended to regulate the civil administration.
            In the Considerations on the Rise and Declension of the Roman Grandeur, we find in what manner Constantine changed the military despotism into a military and civil government, and drew nearer to <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>. There we may trace the different revolutions of this state, and see how they fell from rigour to indolence, and from indolence to impunity.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVI.</chapter>
        <subheading>Of The Just Proportion Betwixt Punishments And Crimes.</subheading>
            <p>
                IT is an essential point, that there should be a certain proportion in punishments, because it is essential that a great crime should be avoided rather than a smaller, and that which is more pernicious to society rather than that which is less.
            “An impostor* , who called himself Constantine Ducas, raised a great insurrection at Constantinople. He was taken and condemned to be whipt; but, upon informing against several persons of distinction, he was sentenced to be burnt as a calumniator.” It is very extraordinary that they should thus proportion the punishments betwixt the crime of high-treason and that of calumny.
            This puts me in mind of a saying of Charles II. king of Great-Britain. He saw a man, one day, standing in the pillory; upon which, he asked what crime the man had committed. He was answered, Please your majesty, he has written a libel against your ministers. The fool! said the king, why did not he write against me? they would have done nothing to him.
            “Seventy persons having conspired against the emperor Basil† , he ordered them to be whipt, and the hair of their heads and beards to be burnt. A stag, one day, having taken hold of him by the girdle with his horn, one of his retinue drew his sword, cut the girdle, and saved him; upon which, he ordered that person’s head to be cut off, for having, said he, drawn his sword against his sovereign.” Who could imagine that the same prince could ever have passed two such different judgements?
            It is a great abuse amongst us to condemn to the same punishment a person that only robs on the highway, and another who robs and murders. Surely, for the public security, some difference should be made in the punishment.
            In China, those who add murder to robbery are cut in pieces‡ ; but not so the others: to this difference it is owing, that, though they rob in that country, they never murder.
            In Russia, where the punishment of robbery and murder is the same, they always murder? . The dead, say they, tell no tales.
            Where there is no difference in the penalty, there should be some in the expectation of pardon. In England they never murder on the highway, because robbers have some hopes of transportation, which is not the case in respect to those that commit murder.
            Letters of grace are of excellent use in moderate governments. This power which the prince has of pardoning, exercised with prudence, is capable of producing admirable effects. The principle of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, which neither grants nor receives any pardon, deprives it of these advantages.
            </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Rack.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE wickedness of mankind makes it necessary for the laws to suppose them better than they really are. <justice type="prosecution">Hence the deposition of two witnesses is sufficient in the punishment of all crimes</justice>. The law believes them, as if they spoke by the mouth of truth. Thus we judge that every child conceived in wedlock is legitimate; the law having a confidence in the mother, as if she were chastity itself. <justice type="cruel_and_unusual_punishment">But the use of the rack against criminals cannot be defended on a like plea of necessity.</justice>
            We have before us the example of a nation, blessed with an excellent civil government§ , where, without any inconveniency, the practice of racking criminals is rejected. It is not, therefore, in its own nature, necessary¶ .
            <justice type="cruel_and_unusual_punishment">So many men of learning and genius have written against the custom of torturing criminals, that after them I durst not presume to meddle with the subject. I was going to say, that it might suit despotic states, where whatever inspires fear is the properest spring of government; I was going to say, that the slaves among the Greeks and Romans — But nature cries out aloud, and asserts her rights.</justice>
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XVIII.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Pecuniary And Corporal Punishments.</subheading>
        <p>
            OUR ancestors, the Germans, admitted of none but pecuniary punishments. Those free and warlike people were of opinion, that their blood ought not to be spilt but with sword in hand. On the contrary, these punishments are rejected by the Japanese* , under pretence that the rich might elude them. But are not the rich afraid of being stripped of their property? And might not pecuniary penalties be proportioned to people’s fortunes? And, in fine, might not infamy be added to those punishments?
            <justice type="due_process">A good legislator takes a just medium; he ordains neither always pecuniary, nor always corporal, punishments.</justice>        
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XIX.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Law Of Retaliation.</subheading>
        <p>
            THE use of the law of retaliation† is very frequent in despotic countries, where they are fond of simple laws. Moderate governments admit of it sometimes; but with this difference, that the former exercise it in full rigour, whereas, among the latter, it ever receives some kind of limitation.
            The law of the twelve tables admitted two; first, <justice type="cruel_and_unusual_punishment">it never condemned to retaliation but when the plaintiff could not be satisfied in any other manner</justice>‡ : secondly, after condemnation they might pay damages and interest? , and then the corporal was changed into a pecuniary punishment§ .
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XX.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Punishment Of Fathers For The Crimes Of Their Children.</subheading>
        <p>
            IN China, <justice type="cruel_and_unusual_punishment">fathers are punished for the crimes of their children</justice>. This was likewise the custom of Peru¶ ; <laws type="religiously_driven">a custom derived from the notion of despotic power.</laws>
            Little does it signify to say, that, in China, the father is punished for not having exerted that paternal authority which nature has established and the laws themselves have improved. This still supposes that there is no honour among the Chinese. Amongst us, parents, whose children are condemned by the laws of their country, and children* , whose parents have undergone the like fate, are as severely punished by shame, as they would be, in China, by the loss of their lives.
        </p>
        
        <chapter>CHAP. XXI.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Clemency Of The Prince.</subheading>
        <p>
            CLEMENCY is the characteristic of monarchs. In republics, whose principle is virtue, it is not so necessary. In <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> governments, where fear predominates, it is less customary, because the great men are to be restrained by examples of severity. It is more necessary in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, where they are governed by honour, which frequently requires what the very law forbids. Disgrace is here equivalent to chastisement; and even the forms of justice are punishments. This is because particular kinds of penalty are formed by shame, which on every side invades the delinquent.
            The great men, in <governments type="monarchial">monarchies</governments>, are so heavily punished by disgrace, by the loss (though often imaginary) of their fortune, credit, acquaintances, and pleasures, that rigour, in respect to them, is needless: it can tend only to divest the subject of the affection he has for the person of his prince, and of the respect he ought to have for public posts and employments.
            As the instability of the great is natural to a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, so their security is interwoven with the nature of <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>.
            So many are the advantages which monarchs gain by clemency, so greatly does it raise their fame and endear them to their subjects, that it is generally happy for them to have an opportunity of displaying it; which, in this part of the world, is seldom wanting.
            Some branch, perhaps, of their authority, but never hardly the whole, will be disputed: and, if they sometimes fight for their crown, they do not fight for their life.
            But some may ask, When is it proper to punish, and when to pardon? — This is a point easier felt than prescribed. When there is danger in the exercise of clemency, it is visible: nothing so easy as to distinguish it from that imbecillity which exposes princes to contempt and to the very incapacity of punishing.
            The emperor Maurice† made a resolution never to spill the blood of his subjects. Anastasius‡ punished no crimes at all. Isaac Angelus took an oath, that no one should be put to death during his reign. Those Greek emperors had forgot that it was not for nothing they were intrusted with the sword.
    </p>
    </book>
</SOL>