<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="spirit_of_laws_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<SOL>
    
<title>THE SPIRIT OF LAWS.</title> 

    <book>
        <heading>BOOK I. OF LAWS IN GENERAL.</heading>
        
            <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Relation Of Laws To Different Beings.</subheading>
        
    <p>
        <laws type="general">LAWS, in their most general signification, are the necessary relations arising from the nature of things.</laws> In this sense, all beings have their [laws]; <laws type="religiously_driven">the Deity his* [laws]</laws>, the material world its [laws], the intelligence superior to man their [laws], the beasts their [laws], man his [laws].
    They who assert, that a blind fatality produced the various effects we behold in this world, talk very absurdly; for can any thing be more unreasonable than to pretend that a blind fatality could be productive of intelligent beings?
    There is then a primitive reason; <religious type="idea_or_belief">and [laws] are the relations subsisting between it and different beings, and the relations of these to one another.
    God is related to the universe as creator and preserver:</religious> the [laws] by which he created all things are those by which he preserves them. He acts according to these rules, because he knows them; he knows them, because he made them; and he made them, because they are relative to his wisdom and power.
    Since we observe that the world, though formed by the motion of matter, and void of understanding, subsists through so long a succession of ages, its motions must certainly be directed by invariable [laws]: and, could we imagine another world, it must also have constant rules, or it would inevitably perish.
    Thus the creation, which seems an arbitrary act, supposeth [laws] as invariable as those of the fatality of the atheists. It would be absurd to say, that the Creator might govern the world without those rules, since without them it could not subsist.
    <laws type="fixed">These rules are a fixed and invariable relation.</laws> In bodies moved, the motion is received, increased, diminished, lost, according to the relations of the quantity of matter and velocity: each diversity is uniformity; each change is constancy.
    Particular intelligent beings may have [laws] of their own making; but they have some likewise which they never made. Before there were intelligent beings, they were possible; they had therefore possible relations, and consequently possible [laws]. Before [laws] were made, there were relations of possible justice. To say that there is nothing just or unjust, but what is commanded or forbidden by positive [laws], is the same as saying that, before the describing of a circle, all the radii were not equal.
    We must therefore acknowledge relations of justice antecedent to the positive law by which they are established: as for instance, that, if human societies existed, it would be right to conform to their [laws]; if there were intelligent beings that had received a benefit of another being, they ought to shew their gratitude; if one intelligent being had created another intelligent being, the latter ought to continue in its original state of dependence; if one intelligent being injures another, it deserves a retaliation; and so on.
    But the intelligent world is far from being so well governed as the physical: for, though the former has also its [laws], which of their own nature are invariable, it does not conform to them so exactly as the physical world. This is because, on the one hand, particular intelligent beings are of a finite nature, and consequently liable to error; and, on the other, their nature requires them to be free agents. Hence they do not steadily conform to their primitive [laws]; and even those of their own instituting they frequently infringe.
    Whether brutes be governed by the general [laws] of motion, or by a particular movement, we cannot determine. Be that as it may, they have not a more intimate relation to God than the rest of the material world; and sensation is of no other use to them, than in the relation they have either to other particular beings, or to themselves.
    <natural_law type="pursuit_of_happiness">By the allurement of pleasure they preserve the individual</natural_law>, and by the same allurement they preserve their species. They have natural [laws], because they are united by sensation; positive [laws] they have none, because they are not connected by knowledge: and yet they do not invariably conform to their natural [laws]: these are better observed by vegetables, that have neither understanding nor sense.
    Brutes are deprived of the high advantages which we have; but they have some which we have not. They have not our hopes; but they are without our fears: they are subject, like us, to death, but without knowing it: even most of them are more attentive than we to self-preservation, and do not make so bad a use of their passions.
    <driving_factors type="physical">Man, as a physical being, is, like other bodies, governed by invariable [laws].</driving_factors> <driving_factors type="mental">As an intelligent being, he incessantly transgresses the [laws] established by God, and changes those of his own instituting.</driving_factors> He is left to his private direction, though a limited being, and subject, like all finite intelligences, to ignorance and error: even his imperfect knowledge he loseth; and, as a sensible creature, he is hurried away by a thousand impetuous passions. Such a being might every instant forget his Creator; God has therefore reminded him of his duty by the [laws] of religion. Such a being is liable every moment to forget himself; philosophy has provided against this by the [laws] of morality. Formed to live in society, he might forget his fellow-creatures; legislators have, therefore, by political and civil [laws], confined him to his duty.
   </p>
    
         <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of The Laws Of Nature.</subheading>
        
   <p> ANTECEDENT to the above-mentioned [laws] are those of <natural_law type="life">nature; so called because they derive their force entirely from our frame and existence</natural_law>. In order to have a perfect knowledge of these [laws], we must consider man before the establishment of society; <driving_factors type="societal">the [laws] received in such a state would be those of nature.</driving_factors>
    The law, which, impressing on our minds the idea of a Creator, inclines us toward him, is the first in importance, though not in order, of natural [laws].<rationale type="philosophy"> Man, in a state of nature, would have the faculty of knowing before he had acquired any knowledge.</rationale> Plain it is that his first ideas would not be of a speculative nature: he would think of the preservation of his being before he would investigate its original. Such a man would feel nothing in himself, at first, but impotency and weakness: his fears and apprehensions would be excessive; as appears from instances (were there any necessity of proving it) of savages found in forests* trembling at the motion of a leaf, and flying from every shadow.
    In this state, every man, instead of being sensible of his equality, would fancy himself inferior: there would, therefore, be no danger of their attacking one another; peace would be the first law of nature.
    The natural impulse, or desire, which <person type="Hobbes">Hobbes</person> attributes to mankind, of subduing one another, is far from being well founded. The idea of empire and dominion is so complex, and depends on so many other notions, that it could never be the first which occurred to the human understanding.
    <person type="Hobbes">Hobbes</person> enquires, “For what reason men go armed, and have locks and keys to fasten their doors, if they be not naturally in a state of war?” But is it not obvious, that he attributes to mankind, before the establishment of society, what can happen but in consequence of this establishment, which furnishes them with motives for hostile attacks and self-defence?
    Next to a sense of his weakness, man would soon find that of his wants. Hence, another law of nature would prompt him to seek for nourishment.
    Fear, I have observed, would induce men to shun one another; but the marks of this fear, being reciprocal, would soon engage them to associate. Besides, this association would quickly follow from the very pleasure one animal feels at the approach of another of the same species. Again, the attraction arising from the difference of sexes would enhance this pleasure, and the natural inclination they have for each other would form a third law.
    Beside the sense or instinct which man possesses in common with brutes, he has the advantage of acquired knowledge; and thence arises a second tie, which brutes have not. Mankind have therefore a new motive of uniting, and a fourth law of nature results from the desire of living in society.
         </p>
        <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
            <subheading>Of Positive Laws.</subheading>
        
 <p> <driving_factors type="societal">AS soon as mankind enter into a state of society, they lose the sense of their weakness; equality ceases, and then commences the state of war.</driving_factors>
    Each particular society begins to feel its strength; <driving_factors type="international">whence arises a state of war betwixt different nations</driving_factors>. The individuals likewise of each society become sensible of their force: <rationale type="philosophy">hence the principal advantages of this society they endeavour to convert to their own emolument</rationale>; which constitutes a state of war betwixt individuals.
    <rationale type="logical">These two different kinds of states give rise to human [laws]</rationale>. Considered as inhabitants of so great a planet, which necessarily contains a variety of nations, they have [laws] relative to their mutual intercourse, <rationale type="philosophy">which is what we call the law of nations</rationale>. As members of a society that must be properly supported, <laws type="governmental">they have [laws] relative to the governors and the governed</laws>; and this we distinguish by the name of <rationale type="political">politic law</rationale>. They have also another sort of [laws], as they stand in relation to each other; by which is understood the civil law.
    The law of nations is naturally founded on this principle, that different nations ought in time of peace to do one another all the good they can, and in time of war as little injury as possible, without prejudicing their real interests.
    The object of war is victory; that of victory is conquest; and that of conquest, preservation. From this and the preceding principle all those rules are derived which constitute the law of nations.
    All countries have a law of nations, not excepting the <society type="city_state">Iroquois</society> themselves, though they devour their prisoners; for they send and receive ambassadors, and understand the rights of war and peace. The mischief is, that their law of nations is not founded on true principles.
    Besides the law of nations relating to all societies, there is a polity, or civil <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>, for each, particularly considered. No society can subsist without a form of government. “The united strength of individuals,” as Gravina well observes, “constitutes what we call the body politic.”
    The general strength may be in the hands of a single person, or of many. Some think that, nature having established paternal authority, the most natural government was that of a single person. But the example of paternal authority proves nothing: for, if the power of a father be relative to a single government, that of brothers after the death of a father, and that of cousin-germans after the decease of brothers, refer to a government of many. The political power necessarily comprehends the union of several families.
    Better is it to say, that the government most conformable to nature is that which best agrees with the humour and disposition of the people in whose favour it is established.
    The strength of individuals cannot be united without a conjunction of all their wills. “The conjunction of those wills,” as Gravina again very justly observes, “is what we call the civil state.”
    <rationale type="logical">Law in general is human reason</rationale>, inasmuch as it governs all the inhabitants of the earth; the political and civil [laws] of each nation ought to be only the particular cases in which human reason is applied.
    They should be adapted in such a manner to the people for whom they are framed, that it is a great chance if those of one nation suit another.
    They should be relative to the nature and principle of each government; whether they form it, as may be said of political [laws]; or whether they support it, as in the case of civil institutions.
    They should be relative to the climate of each country, to the quality of its soil, to its situation and extent, to the principal occupation of the natives, whether husbandmen, huntsmen, or shepherds: they should have a relation to the degree of liberty which the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents> will bear, to the religion of the inhabitants, to their inclinations, riches, numbers, commerce, manners, and customs. In fine, they have relations to each other, as also to their origin, to the intent of the legislator, and to the order of things on which they are established; in all which different lights they ought to be considered.
    This is what I have undertaken to perform in the following work. These relations I shall examine, since all these together constitute what I call the Spirit of Laws.
    I have not separated the political from the civil institutions; for, as I do not pretend to treat of [laws], but of their spirit, and as this spirit consists in the various relations which the [laws] may have to different objects, it is not so much my business to follow the natural order of [laws], as that of these relations and objects.
    I shall first examine the relations which [laws] have to the nature and principle of each government: and, as this principle has a strong influence on [laws], I shall make it my study to understand it thoroughly; and, if I can but once establish it, the [laws] will soon appear to flow from thence as from their source. I shall proceed afterwards to other more particular relations.</p>
    
    </book>
    
    <book>
        
        <heading>BOOK II. OF LAWS DIRECTLY DERIVED FROM THE NATURE OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
            <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Nature Of Three Different Governments.</subheading>
        
        <p>THERE are three species of government; <governments type="groups_of_government">republican, monarchical, and despotic</governments>. In order to discover their nature, it is sufficient to recollect the common notion, which supposes three definitions, or rather three facts: 
            “<governments type="republic">That a republican government</governments> is that in which the <rationale type="political"> body or only a part of the people is possessed of the supreme power</rationale>: 
            <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, that in which <rationale type="political">a single person governs by fixed and established [laws]:</rationale> 
            a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, that in which <rationale type="political">a single person directs every thing by his own will and caprice.”</rationale>
        This is what I call the nature of each government: we must now inquire into those [laws] which directly conform to this nature, and consequently are the fundamental institutions.
        </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Republican Government, And The Laws Relative To Democracy.</subheading>
        
       <p> WHEN the body of the people is possessed of the supreme power, this is called a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. When the supreme power is lodged in the hands of a part of the people, it is then an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>.
        In a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> the people are in some respects the sovereign, and in others the subject.
        There can be no exercise of sovereignty but by their <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s, which are their own will: now, the sovereign’s will is the sovereign himself. The [laws], therefore, which establish the right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>, are fundamental to this government. And indeed it is as important to regulate, in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, in what manner, by whom, to whom, and concerning what, <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s are to be given, as it is, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, to know who is the prince, and after what manner he ought to govern.
        Libanius* says, that at “<place type="city">Athens</place> a stranger who intermeddled in the assemblies of the people was punished with death.” This is because such a man usurped the rights of sovereignty.
        It is an essential point, to fix the number of citizens who are to form the public assemblies; otherwise it would be uncertain whether the whole or only a part of the people had given their votes. At Sparta the number was fixed to ten thousand. But <place type="city">Rome</place>, designed by <person type="Providence">Providence</person> to rise from the weakest beginnings to the highest pitch of grandeur; <place type="city">Rome</place>, doomed to experience all the vicissitudes of fortune; <society type="city_state">Rome</society>, who had sometimes all her inhabitants without her walls, and sometimes all <place type="state">Italy</place> and a considerable part of the world within them; <place type="city">Rome</place>, I say, never fixed* the number; and this was one of the principal causes of her ruin.
        The people, in whom the supreme power resides, ought to have the management of every thing within their reach: what exceeds their abilities must be conducted by their ministers.
        But they cannot properly be said to have their ministers, without the power of nominating them: it is therefore a fundamental maxim, in this government, that the people should choose their ministers; that is, their magistrates.
        They have occasion, as well as monarchs, and even more so, to be directed by a council or senate. But, to have a proper confidence in these, they should have the choosing of the members; whether the election be made by themselves, as at <place type="city">Athens</place>; or by some magistrate deputed for that purpose, as on certain occasions was customary at <place type="city">Rome</place>.
        The people are extremely well qualified for choosing those whom they are to intrust with part of their authority. They have only to be determined by things to which they cannot be strangers, and by facts that are obvious to sense. They can tell when a person has fought many battles, and been crowned with success; they are therefore very capable of electing a general. They can tell when a judge is assiduous in his office, gives general satisfaction, and has never been charged with bribery: this is sufficient for choosing a prætor. They are struck with the magnificence or riches of a fellow-citizen: no more is requisite for electing an ædile. These are facts of which they can have better information in a public forum than a monarch in his palace. But are they capable of conducting an intricate affair, of seizing and improving the opportunity and critical moment of action? No; this surpasses their abilities.
        Should we doubt of the people’s natural capacity, in respect to the discernment of merit, we need only cast an eye on the series of surprising elections made by the <society type="city_state">Athenians</society> and <society type="city_state">Romans</society>; which no one surely will attribute to hazard.
        We know that, though the people of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> assumed to themselves the right of raising plebeians to public offices, yet they never would exert this power; and though, at <place type="city">Athens</place>, the magistrates were allowed, by the law of Aristides, to be elected from all the different classes of inhabitants, there never was a case, says Xenophon* , that the common people petitioned for employments which could endanger either their security or their glory.
        As most citizens have sufficient abilities to choose, though unqualified to be chosen, so the people, though capable of calling others to an account for their administration, are incapable of conducting the administration themselves.
        The public business must be carried on, with a certain motion, neither too quick nor too slow. But the motion of the people is always either too remiss or too violent. Sometimes, with a hundred thousand arms, they overturn all before them; and sometimes, with a hundred thousand feet, they creep like insects.
        In a popular state the inhabitants are divided into certain classes. It is in the manner of making this division that great legislators have signalized themselves; and it is on this the duration and prosperity of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> have ever depended.
        <person type="Servius">Servius Tullus</person> followed the spirit of <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> in the distribution of his classes. We find, in Livy,† and in Dionysius Halicarnasseus,‡ in what manner he lodged the right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> in the hands of the principal citizens. He had divided the people of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> into a hundred and ninety-three centuries, which formed six classes; and, ranking the rich, who were in smaller numbers, in the first centuries; and those in middling circumstances, who were more numerous, in the next, he flung the indigent multitude into the last; and, as each century had but one vote* , it was property rather than numbers that decided the elections.
        <person type="Solon">Solon</person> divided the people of <society type="city_state">Athens</society> into four classes. In this he was directed by the spirit of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, his intention not being to fix those who were to choose, but such as were eligible: therefore, leaving to every citizen the right of election, he made† the
        judges eligible from each of those four classes; but the magistrates he ordered to be chosen only out of the first three, consisting of persons of easy fortunes.
        As the division of those who have a right of <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is a fundamental law in <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, the manner also of giving this <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is another fundamental.
        The <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot is natural to <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, as that by choice is to <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>. The <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot is a method of electing that offends no one; but animates each
        citizen with the pleasing hope of serving his country.
        Yet, as this method is in itself defective, it has been the endeavour of the most eminent legislators to regulate and amend it.
        <person type="Solon">Solon</person> made a law, at <place type="city">Athens</place>, that military employments should be conferred by choice; but that senators and judges should be elected by lot.
        The same legislator ordained, that civil magistracies attended with great expence should be given by choice, and the others by lot.
        In order, however, to amend the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot, he made a rule, that none but those who presented themselves should be elected; that the person elected should be examined by judges,* and that every one should have a right to accuse him if he were unworthy of the office† : this participated at the same time of the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> by lot, and of that by choice. When the time of their magistracy was expired, they were obliged to submit to another judgement in regard to their conduct. Persons utterly unqualified must have been extremely backward in giving in their names to be drawn by lot.
        The law which determines the manner of giving <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights> is likewise fundamental in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. It is a question of some importance, whether the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s ought to be public or secret. Cicero observes,‡ that the [laws]? which rendered them secret, towards the close of the <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, were the cause of its decline. But, as this is differently practised in different <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, I shall offer here my thoughts concerning this subject.
        The people’s <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s ought doubtless to be public§ ; and this should be considered as a fundamental law of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. The lower class ought to be directed by those of higher rank, and restrained within bounds by the gravity of eminent personages. Hence, by rendering the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s secret in the <society type="city_state">Roman republic</society>, all was lost: it was no longer possible to direct a populace that sought its own destruction. But, when the body of the nobles are to vote in an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>,* or in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> the senate,† as the business is then only to prevent intrigues, the <rights type="voting">suffrage</rights>s cannot be too secret.
        Intriguing in a senate is dangerous: dangerous it is also in a body of nobles; but not so in the people, whose nature is to act through passion. In countries where they have no share in the government, we often see them as much inflamed on the account of an actor, as ever they could be for the welfare of the state. The misfortune of a <governments type="republic">republic</governments> is, when intrigues are at an end; which happens when the people are gained by bribery and corruption: in this case they grow indifferent to public affairs, and avarice
        becomes their predominant passion. Unconcerned about the government and every thing belonging to it, they quietly wait for their hire.
        It is likewise a fundamental law, in democracies, that <rights type="individual_rights">the people should have the sole power to enact [laws]</rights>. And yet there are a thousand occasions on which it is necessary the <rights type="legislative_rights">senate should have a power of decreeing: nay, it is frequently proper to make some trial of a law before it is established.</rights> The <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>s of <society type="city_state">Rome</society> and <society type="city_state">Athens</society> were excellent. The <rights type="legislative_rights">decrees of the senate‡ had the force of [laws] for the space of a year, but did not become perpetual till they were ratified by the consent of the people.
        </rights>
        </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Laws Relative To The Nature Of Aristocracy.</subheading>
        
        <p>IN an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> the supreme power is lodged in the hands of a certain number of persons. These are invested both with the legislative and executive authority; and the rest of the people are, in respect to them, the same as the subjects of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> in regard to the sovereign.
        They do not vote here by lot; for this would be productive of inconveniencies only. And indeed, in a government where the most mortifying distinctions are already established, though they were to be chosen by lot, still they would not cease to be odious: it is the nobleman they envy, and not the magistrate.
        When the nobility are numerous, there must be a senate to regulate the affairs which the body of nobles are incapable of deciding, and to prepare others for their decision. In this case it may be said, that the <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> is in some measure in the senate, the <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments> in the body of the nobles, and the people are a cypher.
        It would be a very happy thing, in an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>, if the people, in some measure, could be raised from their state of annihilation. Thus, at Genoa, the bank of St. George being administered by the people* gives them a certain influence in the government, from whence their whole prosperity is derived.
        The senators ought by no means to have a right of naming their own members; for this would be the only way to perpetuate abuses. At <place type="city">Rome</place>, which in its early years was a kind of <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>, the senate did not fill up the vacant places in their own body: the new members were nominated by the* censors.
        In a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, the sudden rise of a private citizen to exorbitant power produces <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, or something more than <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>. In the latter, the [laws] have provided for, or in some measure adapted themselves to, the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>; and the principle of government checks the monarch: but, in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, where a private citizen has obtained an exorbitant power,† the abuse of this power is much greater, because the [laws] foresaw it not, and consequently made no provision against it.
        There is an exception to this rule, when the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents> is such as to have immediate need of a magistrate invested with an exorbitant power. Such was <society type="city_state">Rome</society> with her dictators; such is Venice with her state-inquisitors: these are formidable magistrates, who restore, as it were by violence, the state to its liberty. But how comes it that these magistracies are so very different in these two <governments type="republic">republics</governments>? It is because <society type="city_state">Rome</society> supported the remains of her <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> against the people; whereas Venice employs her state-inquisitors to maintain her <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> against the nobles. The consequence was, that at <place type="city">Rome</place> the dictatorship could be only of a short duration, as the people act through passion, and not with design. It was necessary that a magistracy of this kind 
        should be exercised with lustre and pomp; the business being to intimidate, and not to punish, the multitude. It was also proper that the dictator should be created only for some particular affair, and for this only should have an unlimited authority, as he was always created upon some sudden emergency. On the contrary, at Venice they have occasion for a permanent magistracy; for here it is that schemes may be set on foot, continued, suspended, and resumed; that the ambition of a single person becomes that of a family, and the ambition of one family that of many. They have occasion for a secret magistracy, the crimes they punish being hatched in secrecy and silence. This magistracy must have a general inquisition; for their business is not to remedy known disorders, but to prevent the unknown. In a word, the latter is designed to punish suspected crimes; whereas the former used rather menaces than punishment, even for crimes that were openly avowed.
        In all magistracies the greatness of the power must be compensated by the brevity of the duration. This most legislators have fixed to a year: a longer space would be dangerous, and a shorter would be contrary to the nature of government; for who is it that, in the management even of his domestic affairs, would be thus confined? At Ragusa* the chief magistrate of the <governments type="republic">republic</governments> is changed every month, the other officers every week, and the governor of the castle every day. But this can take place only in a small <governments type="republic">republic</governments> environed† by formidable powers, who might easily corrupt such petty and insignificant magistrates.
        The best <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> is that in which those who have no share in the legislature are so few and inconsiderable, that the governing party have no interest in oppressing them. Thus, when‡ <person type="Antipater">Antipater</person> made a law at <place type="city">Athens</place>, that whosoever was not worth two thousand drachms should have no power to vote, he formed, by this method, the best <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> possible; because this was so small a sum, as excluded very few, and not one of any rank or consideration in the city.
        <governments type="aristocracy">Aristocratical</governments> families ought, therefore, as much as possible, to level themselves, in appearance, with the people. The more an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> borders on <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>, the nearer it approaches to perfection; and, in proportion as it draws towards <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, the more it is imperfect.
        But the most imperfect of all is that in which the part of the people that obeys is in a state of civil servitude to those who command; as the <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments> of Poland, where the peasants are slaves to the nobility.
        </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Relation Of Laws To The Nature Of Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        
        <p>THE intermediate, subordinate, and dependent powers constitute the nature of <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> government; I mean of that in which a single person governs by fundamental [laws]. I said, the intermediate, subordinate, and dependent powers: and indeed, in monarchies, the prince is the source of all power, political and civil. These fundamental [laws] necessarily suppose the intermediate channels through which the power flows; for, if there be only the momentary and capricious will of a single person to govern the state, nothing can be fixed, and of course there is no fundamental law.
        The most natural intermediate and subordinate power is that of the nobility. This, in some measure, seems to be essential to a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, whose fundamental maxim is, No monarch, no nobility; no nobility, no monarch: but there may be a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> prince.
        There are men who have endeavoured, in some countries in Europe, to suppress the jurisdiction of the nobility; not perceiving that they were driving at the very thing that was done by the parliament of England. Abolish the privileges of the lords, the clergy, and cities, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, and you will soon have a popular state, or else a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government.
        The courts of a considerable kingdom in Europe have, for many ages, been striking at the patrimonial jurisdiction of the lords and clergy. We do not pretend to censure these sage magistrates; but we leave it to the public to judge how far this may alter the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>.
        Far am I from being prejudiced in favour of the privileges of the clergy; however, I should be glad their jurisdiction were once fixed. The question is not, whether their jurisdiction was justly established; but, whether it be really established; whether it constitutes a part of the [laws] of the country, and is in every respect relative to those [laws]; whether, between two powers acknowledged independent, the conditions ought not to be reciprocal; and whether it be not equally the duty of a good subject to defend the prerogative of the prince, and to maintain the limits which from time immemorial he has prescribed to his authority.
        Though the ecclesiastic power be so dangerous in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, yet it is extremely proper in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, especially of the absolute kind. What would become of Spain and Portugal, since the subversion of their [laws], were it not for this only barrier against the incursions of arbitrary power? a barrier ever useful when there is no other: for, since a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government is productive of the most dreadful calamities to human nature, the very evil that restrains it is beneficial to the subject.
        In the same manner as the ocean, threatening to overflow the whole earth, is stopped by weeds and pebbles, that lie scattered along the shore; so monarchs, whose power seems unbounded, are restrained by the smallest obstacles, and suffer their natural pride to be subdued by supplication and prayer.
        The English, to favour their liberty, have abolished all the intermediate powers of which their <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> was composed. They have a great deal of reason to be jealous of this liberty: were they ever to be so unhappy as to lose it, they would be one of the most servile nations upon earth.
        Mr. Law, through ignorance both of a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> and <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>, was one of the greatest promoters of absolute power ever known in Europe. Besides the violent and extraordinary changes owing to his direction, he would fain suppress all the intermediate ranks, and abolish the political communities. He was dissolving* the <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> by his chimerical reimbursements, and seemed as if he even wanted to redeem the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>.
        It is not enough to have intermediate powers in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>; there must be also a depositary of the [laws]. This depositary can only be the judges of the supreme courts of justice, who promulge the new [laws], and revive the obsolete. The natural ignorance of the nobility, their indolence, and contempt of civil government, require there should be a body invested with a power of reviving and executing the [laws], which would be otherwise buried in oblivion. The prince’s council are not a proper depositary: they are naturally the depositary of the momentary will of the prince, and not of the fundamental [laws]. Besides, the prince’s council is continually changing; it is neither permanent nor numerous; neither has it a sufficient share of the confidence of the people; consequently it is incapable to set them right in difficult conjunctures, or to reduce them to proper obedience.
        Despotic governments, where there are no fundamental [laws], have no such kind of depositary. Hence it is that religion has generally so much influence in those countries, because it forms a kind of permanent depositary; and, if this cannot be said of religion, it may of the customs that are respected instead of [laws].
        </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Laws Relative To The Nature Of A Despotic Government.</subheading>
       <p> 
        FROM the nature of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> power it follows, that the single person, invested with this power, commits the execution of it also to a single person. A man, whom his senses continually inform that he himself is every thing, and his subjects nothing, is naturally lazy, voluptuous, and ignorant. In consequence of this, he neglects the management of public affairs. But, were he to commit the administration to many, there would be continual disputes among them; each would form intrigues to be his first slave, and he would be obliged to take the reins into his own hands. It is, therefore, more natural for him to resign it to a vizir,* and to invest him with the same power as himself. The creation of a vizir is a fundamental law of this government.
        It is related of a pope, that he had started an infinite number of difficulties against his election, from a thorough conviction of his incapacity. At length he was prevailed on to accept of the pontificate, and resigned the administration entirely to his nephew. He was soon struck with surprize, and said, “I should never have thought that these things were so easy.” The same may be said of the princes of the East, who, being educated in a prison, where eunuchs corrupt their hearts and debase their understandings, and where they are frequently kept ignorant of their high rank, when drawn forth in order to be placed on the throne, they are at first confounded; but, as soon as they have chosen a vizir, and abandoned themselves in their seraglio to the most brutal passions, pursuing, in the midst of a prostituted court, every capricious extravagance, they could never have dreamt to find matters so easy.
        The more extensive the empire, the larger the seraglio; and consequently the more voluptuous the prince. Hence the more nations such a sovereign has to rule, the less he attends to the cares of government; the more important his affairs, the less he makes them the subject of his deliberations.</p>
    </book>
    
    <book>
        <heading>BOOK III. OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE THREE KINDS OF GOVERNMENT.</heading>
        
            <chapter>CHAP. I.</chapter>
                <subheading>Difference Between The Nature And Principle Of Government.</subheading>
        
    <p>AFTER having examined the laws relative to the nature of each government, we must investigate those which relate to its principle.
    There is this difference between* the nature and principle of government, that the former is that by which it is constituted, and the latter that by which it is made to act. One is its particular structure, and the other the <human_behavior type="human_nature">human passions</human_behavior> which set it in motion.
    Now, laws ought to be no less relative to the principle, than to the nature, of each government. We must therefore enquire into this principle, which shall be the subject of this third book.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. II.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Principle Of Different Governments.</subheading>
        
    <p>I have already observed, that it is the nature of a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> government, that either the collective body of the people or particular families should be possessed of the supreme power: of a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, that the prince should have this power, but, in the execution of it, should be directed by established laws: of a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, that a single person should rule according to his own will and caprice. This enables me to discover their three principles, which are naturally derived from thence. I shall begin with a <governments type="republic">republican</governments> government, and in particular with that of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>.
    </p>
    `   <chapter>CHAP. III.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Principle Of Democracy.</subheading>
        
   <p> THERE is no great share of probity necessary to support a <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> or <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government: the force of laws, in one, and the prince’s arm, in the other, are sufficient to direct and maintain the whole: but, in a popular state, one spring more is necessary, namely, <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
    What I have here advanced is confirmed by the unanimous testimony of historians, and is extremely agreeable to the nature of things. For, it is clear, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, where he, who commands the execution of the laws, generally thinks himself above them, there is less need of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> than in a popular government, where the person, entrusted with the execution of the laws, is sensible of his being subject to their direction.
    Clear it is, also, that a monarch, who, through bad advice or indolence, ceases to enforce the execution of the laws, may easily repair the evil; he has only to follow other advice, or to shake off this indolence. But when, in a popular government, there is a suspension of the laws, (as this can proceed only from the corruption of the republic,) the state is certainly undone.
    A very droll spectacle it was, in the last century, to behold the impotent efforts of the English towards the establishment of <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. As they, who had a share in the direction of public affairs, were void of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>; as their ambition was enflamed by the success of the most daring of their members† ; as the prevailing parties were successively animated by the spirit of faction; the government was continually changing; the people, amazed at so many revolutions, in vain attempted to erect a commonwealth. At length, when the country had undergone the most violent shocks, they were obliged to have recourse to the very government which they had so wantonly proscribed.
    When <person type="Sylla">Sylla</person> thought of restoring <society type="city_state">Rome</society> to her liberty, this unhappy city was incapable of that blessing. She had only the feeble remains of <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which were continually diminishing: instead of being roused out of her lethargy by Cæsar, Tiberius, Caius, Claudius, Nero, Domitian, she riveted every day her chains; if she struck some blows, her aim was at the tyrant, but not at the usurpation.
    The politic <society type="state_group">Greeks</society>, who lived under a popular government, knew no other support than <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>: the modern inhabitants of that country are entirely taken up with manufacture, commerce, finances, opulence, and luxury.
    When <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is banished, ambition invades the minds of those who are disposed to receive it, and avarice possesses the whole community. The objects of their desires are changed; what they were fond of before is become indifferent; they were free
    while under the restraint of laws, but they would fain now be free to act against law; and, as each citizen is like a slave who has run away from his master, what was a maxim of equity, he calls rigour; what was a rule of action, he stiles constraint; and to precaution he gives the name of fear. Frugality, and not the thirst of gain, now passes for avarice. Formerly, the wealth of individuals constituted the public treasure, but now this is become the patrimony of private persons. The members of the commonwealth riot on the public spoils, and its strength is only the power of a few and the licentiousness of many.
    <society type="city_state">Athens</society> was possessed of the same number of forces, when she triumphed so gloriously, and when, with so much infamy, she was inslaved. She had twenty thousand citizens§ when she defended the <society type="state_group">Greeks</society> against the <society type="state_group">Persians</society>, when she contended for empire with <society type="city_state">Sparta</society>, and invaded <place type="city">Sicily</place>. She had twenty thousand when <person type="Demetrius">Demetrius Phalereus</person> numbered them* , as slaves are told by the head in a market- place. When <person type="Philip">Philip</person> attempted to lord it over <place type="state">Greece</place>, and appeared at the gates of <place type="city">Athens</place>† , she had even then lost nothing but time. We may see, in <person type="Demosthenes">Demosthenes</person>, how difficult it was to awake her: she dreaded <person type="Philip">Philip</person>, not as the enemy of her liberty, but of her pleasures? . This famous city, which had withstood so many defeats, and, after having been so often destroyed, had as often risen out of her ashes, was overthrown at <place type="city">Chæronea</place>, and, at one blow, deprived of all hopes of resource. What does it avail her, that <person type="Philip">Philip</person> sends back her prisoners, if he does not return her men? It was ever after as easy to triumph over the <society type="city_state">Athenian</society> forces as it had been difficult to subdue her <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
    How was it possible for <place type="area">Carthage</place> to maintain her ground? When <person type="Hannibal">Hannibal</person>, upon his being made prætor, endeavoured to hinder the magistrates from plundering the <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, did not they complain of him to the <society type="city_state">Romans</society>? Wretches, who would fain be citizens without a city, and beholden for their riches to their very destroyers! <society type="city_state">Rome</society> soon insisted upon having three hundred of their principal citizens as hostages; she obliged them next to surrender their arms and ships; and then she declared war† . From the desperate efforts of this defenceless city, one may judge of what she might have performed in her full vigour, and assisted by <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. IV.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Principle Of Aristocracy.</subheading>
        
    <p>AS <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is necessary in a popular government, it is requisite, also, under an <governments type="aristocracy">aristocracy</governments>. True it is, that, in the latter, it is not so absolutely requisite.
    The people, who, in respect to the nobility, are the same as the subjects with regard to a monarch, are restrained by their laws: they have, therefore, less occasion for <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> than the people in a <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. But how are the nobility to be restrained? They, who are to execute the laws against their colleagues, will immediately perceive they are acting against themselves. Virtue is, therefore, necessary in this body, from the very nature of the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>.
    An aristocratical government has an inherent vigour, unknown to <governments type="democratic">democracy</governments>. The nobles form a body, who, by their prerogative, and for their own particular interest, restrain the people; it is sufficient, that there are laws in being, to see them executed.
    But, easy as it may be for the body of the nobles to restrain the people, it is difficult to restrain themselves* . Such is the nature of this <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>, that it seems to subject the very same persons to the power of the laws, and, at the same time, to exempt them.
    Now, such a body as this can restrain itself only two ways; either by a very eminent <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which puts the nobility, in some measure, on a level with the people, and may be the means of forming a great <governments type="republic">republic</governments>; or by an inferior <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, which puts them, at least, upon a level with one another; and on this their preservation depends.
    Moderation is, therefore, the very soul of this government; a moderation, I mean, founded on <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, not that which proceeds from indolence and pusillanimity.
    </p>
         <chapter>CHAP. V.</chapter>
               <subheading>That Virtue Is Not The Principle Of A Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        
    <p>IN monarchies, policy effects great things with as little <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> as possible. Thus, in the nicest machines, art has reduced the number of movements, springs, and wheels.
    The state subsists independently of the love of our country, of the thirst of true glory, of self-denial, of the sacrifice of our dearest interests, and of all those heroic <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s which we admire in the ancients, and to us are known only by story.
    The laws supply here the place of those <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s; they are by no means wanted, and the state dispenses with them: an action, performed here in secret, is, in some measure, of no consequence.
    Though all crimes be, in their own nature, public, yet there is a distinction between crimes really public and those that are private, which are so called, because they are more injurious to individuals than to the community.
    Now, in <governments type="republic">republics</governments>, private crimes are more public; that is, they attack the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents> more than they do individuals: and, in monarchies, public crimes are more private; that is, they are more prejudicial to private people than to the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents>.
    I beg that no one will be offended with what I have been saying; my observations are founded on the unanimous testimony of historians. I am not ignorant that virtuous princes are no such very rare instances; but I venture to affirm, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, it is extremely difficult for the people to be virtuous* .
    Let us compare what the historians of all ages have asserted concerning the courts of monarchs; let us recollect the conversations and sentiments of people of all countries in respect to the wretched character of courtiers; and we shall find, that these are not airy speculations, but truths, confirmed by a sad and melancholy experience.
    Ambition in idleness, meanness mixed with pride, a desire of riches without industry, aversion to truth, flattery, perfidy, violation of engagements, contempt of civil duties, fear of the prince’s <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, hope from his weakness, but, above all, a perpetual ridicule cast upon <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, are, I think, the characteristics by which most courtiers, in all ages and countries, have been constantly distinguished. Now, it is exceeding difficult for the leading men of the nation to be knaves, and the inferior sort to be honest; for the former to be cheats, and the latter to rest satisfied with being only dupes.
    But, if there should chance to be some unlucky honest man† among the people, cardinal Richelieu, in his political testament, seems to hint that a prince should take
    care not to employ him‡ . So true is it, that <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is not the spring of this government. It is not, indeed, excluded, but it is not the spring of government.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. VI.</chapter>
                <subheading>In What Manner Virtue Is Supplied In A Monarchical Government.</subheading>
        
   <p> BUT it is high time for me to have done with this subject, lest I should be suspected of writing a satire against <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> government. Far be it from me; if <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> wants one spring, it is provided with another. Honour, that is, the prejudice of every person and rank, supplieth the place of the political <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> of which I have been speaking, and is every where her representative: here it is capable of inspiring the most glorious actions, and, joined with the force of laws, may lead us to the end of government as well as <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> itself.
    Hence, in well-regulated monarchies, they are almost all good subjects, and very few good men; for, to be a good man† , a good intention is necessary* , and we should love our country not so much on our own account as out of regard to the community.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. VII.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Principle Of Monarchy.</subheading>
        
   <p> A <governments type="monarchial">monarchical government</governments> supposeth, as we have already observed, pre-eminences and ranks, as likewise a noble descent. Now, since it is<human_behavior type="human_nature"> the nature</human_behavior> of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> to aspire to preferments and titles, it is properly placed in this government.
    <human_behavior type="human_nature">Ambition is pernicious</human_behavior> in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>; but in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments> it has some good effects; <rationale type="political">it gives life to the government</rationale>, and <rationale type="philosophy">is attended with this advantage, that it is no way dangerous, because it may be continually checked</rationale>.
    It is with this kind of government as with the system of the universe, in which there <rationale type="philosophy">is a power that constantly repels all bodies from the center</rationale>, and a power of gravitation, that attracts them to it. Honour sets all the parts of the body politic in motion, and, by its very action, connects them; thus each individual advances the public good, while he only thinks of promoting his own interest.
    True it is, that, philosophically speaking, it is a false <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> which moves all the parts of the government; but even this false <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> is as useful to the public as true <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> could possibly be to private people.
    Is it not a very great point, to oblige men to perform the most difficult actions, such as require an extraordinary exertion of fortitude and resolution, without any other recompence than that of glory and applause?
   </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. VIII.</chapter>
                <subheading>That Honour Is Not The Principle Of Despotic Government.</subheading>
        
   <p> <characteristics type="ideals">HONOUR</characteristics> is far from being the principle of <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments>: mankind being here all upon a level, <natural_law type="equality">no one person can prefer himself to another</natural_law>; and as, on the other hand, <rationale type="logical">they are all slaves, they can give themselves no sort of preference.</rationale>
    Besides, as <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> has its laws and rules; as it knows not how to submit; as it depends, in a great measure, <rationale type="philosophy">on a man’s own caprice, and not on that of another person;</rationale> it can be <governments type="nationally_governed">found only in countries </governments> in which the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents> is fixed, and where they are governed by settled laws.
    How can despotism bear with <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>? This glories in the contempt of life, and that is founded in the power of taking it away. How can <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, on the other hand, bear with despotism? The former has its fixed rules and peculiar caprices, but the latter is directed by no rule, and its own caprices are subversive of all others.
    Honour, therefore, a thing unknown in arbitrary governments, some of which have not even a proper word to express it* , is the prevailing principle in monarchies; here it gives life to the whole body politic, to the laws, and even to the <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>s themselves.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. IX.</chapter>
                <subheading>Of The Principle Of Despotic Government.</subheading>
        
    <p>AS <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics> is necessary in a <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, and, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, so fear is necessary in a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments>: with regard to <characteristics type="ideals">virtue</characteristics>, there is no occasion for it, and <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> would be extremely dangerous.
    Here, the immense power of the prince is devolved intirely upon those whom he is pleased to intrust with the administration. Persons, capable of setting a value upon themselves, would be likely to create disturbances. Fear must, therefore, depress their spirits, and extinguish even the least sense of ambition.
    A moderate government may, whenever it pleases, and without the least danger, relax its springs: it supports itself by the laws and by its own internal strength. But, when a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> prince ceases one single moment to lift up his arm, when he cannot instantly demolish those whom he has intrusted with the first employments† , all is over: for, as fear, the spring of this government, no longer subsists, the people are left without a protector.
    It is probably in this sense the Cadis maintained that the Grand Seignior was not obliged to keep his word or oath, when he limited thereby his authority‡ .
    It is necessary that the people should be judged by laws, and the great men by the caprice of the prince; that the lives of the lowest subjects should be safe, and the bashaw’s head ever in danger. We cannot mention these monstrous governments without horror. The <society type="state_group">Sophi of Persia</society>, dethroned, in our days, by Mahomet, the son of Miriveis, saw the <legal_documents type="constitution">constitution</legal_documents> subverted, before this revolution, because he had been too sparing of blood* .
    History informs us, that the horrid cruelties of Domitian struck such a terror into the governors, that the people recovered themselves a little under his reign§ . Thus a torrent overflows one side of a country, and, on the other, leaves fields untouched, where the eye is refreshed by the prospect of fine meadows.
    </p>
            <chapter>CHAP. X.</chapter>
                <subheading>Difference Of Obedience In Moderate And Despotic Governments.</subheading>
        
    <p>IN <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> states, the nature of government requires the most passive obedience; and, when once the prince’s will is made known, it ought infallibly to produce its effect.
    Here they have no limitations or restrictions; no mediums, terms, equivalents, or remonstrances; no change to propose: man is a creature that blindly submits to the absolute will of the sovereign.
    In a country like this, they are no more allowed to represent their apprehensions of a future danger than to impute their miscarriage to the capriciousness of fortune. Man’s portion here, like that of beasts, is instinct, compliance, and punishment.
    Little does it then avail to plead the sentiments of nature, filial respect, conjugal or parental tenderness, the laws of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, or want of health; the order is given, and that is sufficient.
    In <place type="state">Persia</place>, when the king has condemned a person, it is no longer lawful to mention his name or to intercede in his favour. Even if the prince were intoxicated, or non compos, the decree must be executed* ; otherwise he would contradict himself, and the law admits of no contradiction. This has been the way of thinking in that country in all ages: as the order, which Ahasuerus gave, to exterminate the Jews, could not be revoked, they were allowed the liberty of defending themselves.
    One thing, however, may be sometimes opposed to the prince’s will§ , namely, religion. They will abandon, nay, they will slay, a parent, if the prince so commands, but he cannot oblige them to drink wine. The laws of religion are of a superior nature, because they bind the sovereign as well as the subject. But, with respect to the law of nature, it is otherwise; the prince is no longer supposed to be a man.
    In <governments type="monarchial">monarchical</governments> and moderate states, the power is limited by its very spring, I mean, by <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>, which, like a monarch, reigns over the prince and his people. They will not alledge to their sovereign, the laws of religion; a courtier would be apprehensive of rendering himself ridiculous. But the laws of <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> will be appealed to on all occasions. Hence arise the restrictions necessary to obedience: <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics> is naturally subject to whims, by which the subject’s submission will be ever directed.
    Though the manner of obeying be different, in these two kinds of government, the power is the same. On which side soever the monarch turns, he inclines the scale, and is obeyed. The whole difference is, that, in a <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, the prince receives instruction, at the same time that his ministers have greater abilities, and are more versed in public affairs, than the ministers of a <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government.
    </p>
        <chapter>CHAP. XI.</chapter>
            <subheading>>Reflections On The Preceding Chapters.</subheading>
        
    <p><separation_of_powers type="generally_referenced">SUCH are the principles of the three sorts of government</separation_of_powers>: which does not imply, that, in a particular <governments type="republic">republic</governments>, they actually are, but that they ought to be, virtuous: nor does it prove, that, in a particular <governments type="monarchial">monarchy</governments>, they are actuated by <characteristics type="ideals">honour</characteristics>; or, in a particular <governments type="despotic">despotic</governments> government, by fear; but that <rationale type="political">they ought to be directed by these principles, otherwise the government is imperfect.</rationale>
    </p>
    </book>
    
</SOL>